<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian family builded by God, directing all governours of families how to act. 1. Gods timber and framing. 2. Gods foundation and upper building. 3. Gods finishing. 4. Gods furnishing. The sum whereof is shewed after the epistle. By Robert Abbott, Pastour of the Church of God at Austines, near Pauls gate in Watling-street in London.</title>
            <author>Abbot, Robert, 1588?-1662?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75929</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A68</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1233_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6379</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872977</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872977</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75929)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 170:E1233[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian family builded by God, directing all governours of families how to act. 1. Gods timber and framing. 2. Gods foundation and upper building. 3. Gods finishing. 4. Gods furnishing. The sum whereof is shewed after the epistle. By Robert Abbott, Pastour of the Church of God at Austines, near Pauls gate in Watling-street in London.</title>
                  <author>Abbot, Robert, 1588?-1662?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 106 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.L. for Philemon Stephens, at the gilded Lion in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "Gods timber .. furnishing" are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "ffebr. 14 1652."; the '3' in imprint date is crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Family --  Religious life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169476:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Christian</hi> FAMILY <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ILDED BY GOD,</hi> Directing all Governours of <hi>Families</hi> how to act.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Gods Timber and framing.</item>
               <item>2. Gods Foundation and upper building.</item>
               <item>3. Gods Finiſhing.</item>
               <item>4. Gods Furniſhing.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The ſum whereof is ſhewed after the Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>BY ROBERT ABBOTT, Paſtour of the Church of God at <hi>Auſtines,</hi> near <hi>Pauls</hi> gate in <hi>Watling-street</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. L.</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens,</hi> at the gilded Lion in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169476:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169476:2"/>
            <head>TO His dearly beloved FLOCK, my good people of <hi>Auſtines</hi> near <hi>Paul's</hi> ſtump in <hi>London,</hi> ROBERT ABBOTT Their aged and unworthy Paſtour, humbly wiſheth all happineſſe, <hi>Externall, Internall, Eternall.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly beloved in Chriſt our common SAVIOUR.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know not how little time I ſhall be with you here; nor how ſoon <hi>I ſhall goe home, and be no more ſeen.</hi> I ſpeak not this of going to another place (I am weary with tumbling;) or of not being ſeen among you here: but of <hi>going the way of all</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:169476:3"/> 
               <hi>the earth,</hi> and not being ſeen <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of the living.</hi> The Iewes in the midſt of their worſt troubles (except the laſt) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained that they had no <hi>Prophet,</hi> none that could tell them <hi>how long.</hi> I complain not, becauſe it is an advantage not to know that time, that I may expect and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for it every day: but I am ſure that none, except God be pleaſed to reveal it, can tell my time of abode in <hi>this earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle.</hi> I have now lived two, above the great <hi>Clymacterieall</hi> year: and it is a great wonder to me, that amidſt ſo many vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, and ſadding griefes of mind; ſo many troubles, and toſsings of body, and ſo many weakneſses of mould, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, I ſhould live even to this houre.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169476:3"/>
            <p> But <hi>God</hi> will have it ſo, who ſtill <hi>cuts out ſome work for me to do.</hi> I am humbly content, and doe with all chearfulneſſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to our good <hi>God's</hi> pleaſure. <hi>Though I deſire reſt, yet I refuſe not labour</hi> at his command, or at his pointing providence.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe that three things might put my heart upon the wing to be gone to my <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the burthen of <hi>Croſses,</hi> the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the <hi>Churches afflictions,</hi> and the burthen of <hi>Impotent age:</hi> and two things might diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage me from any further work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this ſhop below, the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> of the <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> and the pooreneſſe of the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that <hi>Miniſters</hi> have from the moſt that hear them.</p>
            <p>But when I looke upon the <hi>place</hi> where God hath unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly
<pb facs="tcp:169476:4"/> pitched me, and the <hi>loving perſons</hi> (for the greater part) over whom God hath made me an <hi>Overſeer;</hi> as I doe, <hi>from Lords day to Lords day,</hi> chearfully work for the good of your ſouls (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides at other private opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to doe you good:) So am I willing <hi>(as I am able)</hi> to leave ſome teſtimoniall of my love to you, and care over you, when I have <hi>made my bed in darkneſſe.</hi> If our good God, <hi>In whoſe hands are our dayes, and wayes,</hi> ſhall adde years to my <hi>few and evill dayes,</hi> I may be able by his bleſſed aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to ſhew it in ſome more ſpirituall, and valuable piece. In the mean time, <hi>as I am,</hi> ſo is this <hi>little Book,</hi> which I here preſent, <hi>yours.</hi> And if it may ſet you but one ſtaff or round, in the ladder of life nearer to your happy jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes
<pb facs="tcp:169476:4"/> end, I ſhall abundantly rejoyce over you, and in you.</p>
            <p>You know that the firſt govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ever was in this world was in a <hi>Family;</hi> and the firſt diſorder that ever was in the world was in a <hi>Family;</hi> and all the diſorders that ever fell out ſince, ſprung from <hi>Families.</hi> If <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> had been better, Churches and Common-wealths all along had proſpered. As we read it was in <hi>Athens</hi> of old, the boy ruled the mother, the mother ruled the father, and he ruled the whole City, and thence ſprung many diſorders which made thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent times ſick of them even to complaining: ſo hath it been in all ages, and I am ſure it hath been in ours, all we that live here groan under it ſtill, even to more then a complaint.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169476:5"/>
            <p> Had <hi>young,</hi> and <hi>old,</hi> been right ſet before they entered into a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily:</hi> Had the <hi>Family</hi> been foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in <hi>marriage in the Lord.</hi> Had relations betwixt <hi>wife</hi> and <hi>hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, children</hi> and <hi>parents, ſervants</hi> and <hi>maſters</hi> been holily carried on according to the <hi>rule of Chriſt.</hi> Had the houſe been furniſhed with a wiſe, holy, and carefull <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>mother</hi> of the family: had it been furniſhed with a juſt <hi>get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> and <hi>giving,</hi> it had bin a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times better with Church, Common-wealth, and Family, then it hath been, or is yet. To this end (Chriſtians) have I ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken this little pains; firſt by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, then by writing, to preſent this little Treatiſe unto you. Read it over ſeriouſly between God and your own ſouls, and when you find any touch of it to ſtrike
<pb facs="tcp:169476:5"/> upon any ſtring in your hearts, ſee what may be done to make your Families better, and <hi>Doe it.</hi> It may be ye have been <hi>rotten tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> when you were put into the Family: Oh pray that <hi>the Sonne of Righteouſneſſe would come and bring healing under his wings.</hi> Or it may be, when you were young or old, you have not been made ſuitable to the Word <hi>of God,</hi> pray that now he would <hi>write his Law in your hearts</hi> to make an <hi>alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> by an <hi>application</hi> of the work of the Spirit. Or it may be you have not laid a good founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a Family, by <hi>Marriage in the Lord,</hi> but have married for money, or luſt: pray that God would forget that, and give an <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſtabliſhment</hi> to that which was wickedly done at firſt. Or it may be you have faithleſly, and
<pb facs="tcp:169476:6"/> unconſcionably carried your ſelves in your relations: pray for <hi>union with Chriſt,</hi> to purge out the wickedneſſe of nature, and, with hearty ſorrow for what is paſt, you will ſtand faſt in all your rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions hereafter. Or it may be for want of a good <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres,</hi> there hath been no good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the Family, either every day, or on the <hi>Lords day:</hi> pray that God would rule in their hearts, that God may rule in their houſe, till they may be ſaluted, <hi>The Church that is in thy houſe.</hi> Or it may be for want of true juſtice, both in <hi>lending, borrowing, buying, ſelling, letting, hiring,</hi> and <hi>giving,</hi> the <hi>wages of iniquitie are yet in your houſes:</hi> Oh pray that there be not ſelf-ſeeking, nor deceit, <hi>no, coloured covetouſneſſe,</hi> nor any thing that ſavours of <hi>injurious evil</hi> to be
<pb facs="tcp:169476:6"/> found amongſt you. If God will bleſſe you by this Book, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means, doe what you can to be <hi>built by God</hi> in your Families. Thus God will <hi>proſper the worke of his own hands</hi> upon you, and bring out of your Families bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to the Church, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, as well as to you. This God requires; this I aimed at among you, and for this, while I am, you ſhall have the prayers (Chriſtians) of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Paſtour for Chriſts ſake, and by his appointment, <hi>ROBERT ABBOTT.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:169476:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169476:7"/>
            <head>The ſum of this following Book, which is in ſtead of a generall Table, referring to every <hi>Section, Pſalme</hi> 127. 1.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1
<list>
                     <item>An Introduction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>(Page</hi> 1.)</item>
                     <item>A Traction: wherein</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1
<list>
                     <item>The <hi>Doctrine</hi> is propounded. <hi>If we would have bleſſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, we muſt get them builded by God. (Sect.</hi> 1.)</item>
                     <item>The Application, where fall 2 <hi>quares,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2
<list>
                     <item>1
<list>
                           <item>What <hi>Gods building</hi> in a Family is</item>
                           <item>1
<list>
                                 <item>Both for matter, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 2.)</item>
                                 <item>And for rule and ſquare,
<list>
                                       <item>1
<list>
                                             <item>The word of God,</item>
                                             <item>Not carnal policy, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 3.)</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2</item>
                     <item>How we may procure it. By having</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1
<list>
                     <item>God's <hi>Timber, Single perſons, (Sect.</hi> 4.) which muſt be framed as they are</item>
                     <item>1
<list>
                           <item>Old men, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 5.)</item>
                           <item>Old women, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 6.)</item>
                           <item>Young men and young women, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 7.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2</item>
                     <item>3</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2
<list>
                     <item>God's <hi>building:</hi> which muſt have</item>
                     <item>1
<list>
                           <item>A <hi>foundation, Marriage in the Lord.</hi> In which we muſt goe along with God,</item>
                           <item>1
<list>
                                 <item>In the <hi>Antecedents</hi>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>1
<list>
                                             <item>A right <hi>choiſe,</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>By right <hi>marks, (S.</hi> 8)</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>In the <hi>concomitants,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>1
<list>
                                       <item>The gift of the <hi>Parents</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>The bleſſing of the <hi>Miniſter,</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>The mutual <hi>rejoycing</hi> of the friends <hi>(S.</hi> 9.)</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2</item>
                                 <item>3</item>
                                 <item>In the <hi>conſequents,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>1
<list>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>Cohabitation,</hi> and</item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>Communion. (Sect.</hi> 10.)</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2</item>
                           <item>3</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:169476:8"/>
                     <item> 2
<list>
                           <item>An <hi>upper building,</hi> which ſtands in 3 relations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt</item>
                           <item>1
<list>
                                 <item>Wife, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 11.)</item>
                                 <item>Husband, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 12.)</item>
                                 <item>Children, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 13.)</item>
                                 <item>Parents, <hi>Sect.</hi> 14.)</item>
                                 <item>Servants, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 15.)</item>
                                 <item>Maſters, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 16.)</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2</item>
                           <item>3</item>
                           <item>4</item>
                           <item>5</item>
                           <item>6</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>3</item>
                     <item>God's <hi>finiſhing</hi> by an orderly government, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 17.) which muſt be executed,</item>
                     <item>1
<list>
                           <item>By a good <hi>Father</hi> of a Family, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 18.)</item>
                           <item>By a good <hi>Mother,</hi> of a Family, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 19.)</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2</item>
                     <item>God's <hi>furniſhing</hi> of a Family,</item>
                     <item>1
<list>
                           <item>By <hi>getting</hi> goods: which is either</item>
                           <item>1
<list>
                                 <item>By <hi>lending, (Sect.</hi> 20.)</item>
                                 <item>By <hi>borrowing, (Sect.</hi> 21.)</item>
                                 <item>By <hi>ſelling, (Sect.</hi> 22.)</item>
                                 <item>By <hi>buying, (Sect.</hi> 23.)</item>
                                 <item>By <hi>letting, (Sect.</hi> 24.)</item>
                                 <item>By <hi>hiring, (Sect.</hi> 25.)</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2</item>
                           <item>3</item>
                           <item>4</item>
                           <item>5</item>
                           <item>6</item>
                           <item>By <hi>giving</hi> goods, <hi>(Sect.</hi> 26.)</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>4</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169476:8"/>
            <head>A FAMILY BUILT BY GOD: Or a <hi>Meditation</hi> to direct Houſholders, how to riſe from the Foundation to the height of a bleſſed <hi>Family.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſalm, 127. 1.</bibl>
               <q>Except the Lord build the houſe, they labour in vain that build it; or are builders of it in it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are fifteen Pſalmes which are called <hi>Pſalmes of Degrees,</hi> and this is one. They follow next to the hundred and nineteenth, and are of excellent uſe upon ſeverall occaſions.</p>
            <p>There were diverſe <hi>ſtaires</hi> up into the <hi>Temple,</hi> and the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> did ſtand higher then the reſt, upon ſome of them, for the better edification of the people, when they ſung them; and they ſay, theſe <hi>Pſalmes</hi> had their names from thence.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſcope</hi> of this Pſalm is, to confirm this general propoſition, <hi>That without Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings the diligent endeavours of men are blaſted.</hi> This the Pſalmiſt demonſtrates by a <hi>Diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:169476:9"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>1</label> by an <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> by a <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and by an <hi>Example.</hi> He <hi>diſtributes</hi> all the labours of men into <hi>publike,</hi> and <hi>private:</hi> in both which he ſhews that there is no good ſucceſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods bleſſing. He <hi>oppoſeth</hi> the carefulleſt worker, who without this bleſſing of God is curſed. He <hi>promiſeth</hi> ſweet contentment to them that work with the bleſſing of God, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>They ſhall have ſleep and reſt as Gods beloved</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>3</label> He <hi>Inſtanceth in children,</hi> who are the nurſery plants both of Church, Common-wealth and Family, yet cannot be obtained with any la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour without Gods bleſſing: therefore above all things we muſt wait upon Gods bleſſing to build the houſe firſt by.</p>
            <p>Gods people were firſt in a <hi>Family,</hi> next in a <hi>Church,</hi> and next in a <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore firſt he mentions the <hi>building of an houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> You will ask, <hi>whether God be become a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter?</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I muſt ſay No: but it is Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by theſe things we know, to bring us to the knowledge of what we know not. For as the word <hi>Houſe</hi> is taken figuratively, for all things that conſtitute, and maintain the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and comfort of a family, as wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſervants, goods of all ſorts within dores, and without. So to <hi>build</hi> ſignifies whatſoever contributes to raiſe up, and enlarge a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by honeſt, and good means; as an help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>wife,</hi> hopefull <hi>children,</hi> faithfull <hi>ſervants,</hi> and well gotten <hi>goods,</hi> and inheritances. Thus <note place="margin">Exod. 1. 21. 1 Chron. 17. 12. 2 Sam. 7. 11.</note> God is ſaid to <hi>make the Aegyptian midwives houſes,</hi> and to <hi>build David an houſe,</hi> over, and over again.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:169476:9"/>
               <head>SECT. 1:</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> HEre then is the Doctrine which (if God pleaſe) I ſhall open and apply unto you, that <hi>If we would have bleſſed Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, we muſt get them builded by God.</hi> Husband, wife, children, ſervants, muſt not be like <hi>rotten poſts,</hi> and as <hi>ſtraw, hay, ſtubble</hi> upon a good foundation; but muſt be builded by God: and the whole ſtate, and houſe muſt be finiſhed, and furniſhed by God. <hi>Nabal</hi> was the <hi>head</hi> of a Family, but a drunken Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure; and ſo not builded by God. <hi>Jezabel</hi> was a main <hi>rib</hi> of the Family; but a painted and perſecuting harlot; and ſo not builded by God. <hi>Cain, Eſau, Adoniah, Abſolon,</hi> were <hi>Couplings</hi> in the Family, but a murtherer, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, rebellious; and ſo not builded by God: <hi>Zihah</hi> was a <hi>tyle</hi> or <hi>rafter</hi> in the Family of <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> but a faithleſſe cheating ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; and ſo, not builded by God. <hi>Dives</hi> his houſe was <hi>furniſhed</hi> with great ſtore of wealth, but if he might go gay, and fare daintily, <hi>he regarded not the afflictions of Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus;</hi> and ſo not builded by God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> Therefore be you <hi>(good Chriſtians)</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to make God the Surveyour, Framer, Joyner; ſole workman in your Families, or elſe no comforting bleſſing comes. The ſpeech of Chriſt reacheth to every thing, <hi>without me ye can do nothing;</hi> Experience teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">John 15. 5.</note> thus much concerning Families. <hi>Abraham</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:169476:10"/> was built by God, and mark what God, ſaith, <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>I know that my ſervant Abraham will teach his Family. Joſhuah</hi> was built by God, and mark what he ſaith, <hi>I and my houſe will ſerve the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 24. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord. Naomi</hi> was built by God, and mark her <note place="margin">Ruth 1. 16. &amp; 3. 1. Heſt. 4. 16. Gen. 24.</note> faithfull care of <hi>Ruth. Heſter</hi> was built by God, and mark her ſpeech, <hi>I and my maids will faſt likewiſe. Eleazar</hi> was built by God, and mark his godly care in his maſters ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
               <p>And if a whole Family be thus built; what a joint ſerving of God is there? Husbands, and wives are faithfull; ſervants are carefull; children are obedient; goods are bleſſed; and then we may ſay, as <hi>Paul, Greet the Church</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 16. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>that is in thy houſe.</hi> Moſt complain (and they have too juſt cauſe) that <hi>husbands</hi> are drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards and tyrants, <hi>wives</hi> are ſtubborn, <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> are diſorderly, <hi>ſervants</hi> are unfaithfull. More complain that there is little charity, much contention, many brawles, flouds of drunkenneſs, vollies of oathes. The reaſon of all is, becauſe they are not built by God. What ſhall I ſay then? ſuffer your ſelves to be builded by God. He will pull down the old ruinous building of ſinne. He will hew you with his own axe, <hi>his Word.</hi> He will lay you upon that good foundation, <hi>Chriſt.</hi> He will make you grow up into an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly building in the <hi>Lord,</hi> and then, <hi>the Lord builds the houſe,</hi> and your labour will not be in vain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169476:10"/>
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <p>BUt to ſettle this upon you, your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences will enquire after two things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>What Gods building in a Family is?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>How you may procure it?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Gods building is a well ordered Family by the Word of God.</hi> Here is the <hi>matter</hi> and form of it; and the <hi>Rule</hi> and ſquare by which it is wrought. The <hi>matter</hi> and form of it is <hi>a well ordered Family,</hi> that is, an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly head, and orderly members having mutuall and fit relations either to others. An <hi>orderly head</hi> is the houſe governour, who can with good conſcience ſay, <hi>I will walk in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 101. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>the uprightneſs of my heart in the middeſt of my houſe.</hi> There are many comely heads, but they are painted ones in reſpect of this, or like that in the Carvers ſhop which had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wit nor brains. <hi>Orderly members</hi> are thoſe that depend upon the head, whether wife, children, or ſervants, that can ſay with a good conſcience as <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Naomi, whether</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ruth 1. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>thou goeſt I will go, where thou lodgeſt I will lodge, thy people ſhall be my people, and thy God, my God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Rule</hi> and ſquare of this Family is <hi>The Word of God. Thorough wiſedome is an houſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 24. 3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>builded, and with understanding it is eſtabliſhed, and with knowledge ſhall the chambers be filled with riches.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> What is this wiſedome? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Not that <hi>of the world,</hi> for that is fooliſhneſs: but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169476:11"/> that <hi>of the Word;</hi> for that iſſues from the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>wiſedome</hi> of the Father; who is <hi>made wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome unto us.</hi> And wonder not at this; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the Word is contained neceſſary and abſolute direction for all in a Family; in which reſpect we may ſay, <hi>I adore the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Scripture.</hi> Yea, the word directs <note place="margin">Plenitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae adoro.</note> not onely, but moulds and ſhapes every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for his imployment. We are like crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and knotty trees by nature: but then comes the Word and ſmoothes us for houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work. Therefore we are very fools when we forſake this Word, which is ſo helpfull. In matters of private worſhip men are ſquared by theit minds, and cuſtomes of forefathers: In matters of Converſation, by examples of men, and practiſe of moſt: In Apparel, by faſhion, be they never ſo diſguiſed: In meat and drink, by appetite: In Recreation, by company: In Traffique, by profit; In gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Riches, by the horſ-leaches of deſires: In their whole government by carnal and worldly policy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> YOu will ſay, May I not uſe policy to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh a good order in my Family? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Yes, as you ſee in the good houſewife, deſcribed <note place="margin">Prov. 31. 15, 16. 2 Chron. 27.</note> by <hi>Bathſhebah;</hi> and in <hi>David,</hi> who had one Officer over his treaſures, another over la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, another over Vineyards, another
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169476:11"/> over Wine, another over Olives, another over Oyle, another over Cattell; and in <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> who had Officers that prepared <note place="margin">Neh. 5. 18.</note> dayly an Oxe, ſheep and birds for him, and his retinue: Alſo in <hi>Solomon</hi> who eſtabliſhed <note place="margin">1 King. 4. 22, 27, 28.</note> care for diet, order for his attendants by moneths. Hence when the <hi>Queen of Shebah</hi> ſaw the meat of his table, the ſitting of his ſervants, the order of his ſervitors, and their apparel, ſhe admired it. O for ſuch policy! Yet take heed of Carnall policy which fights with Gods Word. Therefore obſerve foure rules.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Policy muſt not prejudice the honour of God, as <hi>Davids</hi> did, when he was before <hi>Achiſh,</hi> and ſlavered, and carried himſelf like a fool to the diſhonour of him that choſe him King.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Policy muſt not ptejudice the truth of a good Conſcience, as <hi>Rachels</hi> did, when ſhe had hid her fathers gods in the Camels lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Take heed of faining or lying; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will cry.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Policy muſt not prejudice that juſtice which is due to man. Ye know <hi>Davids</hi> policy to cover his baſeneſs with <hi>Bathſhebah,</hi> and how it fell heavy upon <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah.</hi> Such policies are not ſtrange to us to build our neſts with injuſtice, and to make the moſt of our own, whoſoever pinch; but take heed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Policy muſt not ſtretch further then our callings. In every policy for the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your houſe, you muſt make a double
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169476:12"/> enquiry: Firſt into the thing to be done, whether it be lawfull, or unlawfull: next into your ſelves, whether agreeable to your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings wherein <hi>ye muſt abide.</hi> If your policy go <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.</note> beyond theſe rules, it is carnal, and ſenſual. Therefore remember them; yet ſo ſtill, as the Word of God be your rule, and ſquare of all your intendments, and executions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <p n="2">2. VVE come to the next point, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how you may procure Gods building in your Families? Follow God's metaphor ſtill: from plain things it will be made plain unto you, It is <hi>God's building:</hi> and if you would have it, you muſt have four things:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>God's timber and framing of it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>God's ſetting up of it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>God's finiſhing of it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>God's furniſhing of it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>God's Timber.</hi> As when <hi>Solomon</hi> was to build the Temple, he had his timber, Cedar trees, and Fir trees from <hi>Lebanon:</hi> ſo God muſt have ſingle perſons, who are fit to grow up into a building. Of theſe he ſaith in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, <hi>If they cannot abſtain they muſt marry,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>for it is better to marry then to burn:</hi> Marriage in itſelf is a thing indifferent; but by Gods Ordinance it is farr better then ſingle life.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:169476:12"/> 1. It was ordained in Paradiſe before the fall: As then innocency is better then cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; ſo is that eſtate which God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for it.</p>
               <p n="2">2, It was ordained upon ſerious <hi>conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 18.</note> of the bleſſed Trinitie; let us <hi>make an helper</hi> meet for man: therefore it muſt come as an high bleſſing, and priviledge.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God gave a large bleſſing to this eſtate, ſaying, <hi>Encreaſe and multiply,</hi> that it might be <note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> a Fountain, and Seminary of all other kinds of life in Family, Church, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
               <p>Therefore if man had continued in <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie,</hi> ſingle life had been nothing worth. Yea, as the Jewes ſaid proverbially, <hi>Nothing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Wiemſe.</note> 
                  <hi>is good but a woman: He that hath not a wife, is not a man;</hi> ſo, with all men, a wife had been of ſingular eſteem. But ſince ſin came into the world, to ſome men, ſingle life is better then marriage; It frees a man from many cares in houſhold affaires. It affords more leiſure to purſue heavenly things. It makes preſent neceſſitie of affliction leſs troubleſome. Yet, if God have not given re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved diſpoſitions, againſt the burning luſts of the fleſh, <hi>it is better to marry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You will ſay, <hi>ſuch ſhall have troubles in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 28 Prov. 21. 19 Matth. 19. 11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>fleſh:</hi> and <hi>it is better to dwell in the wilderneſs,</hi> then with a <hi>contentious woman in a wide houſe.</hi> It is true, yet <hi>all are not able to receive it,</hi> but they to whom it is given.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> You will ſay, that you will pray to God
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169476:13"/> that he would grant you the gift of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Do; and it is good if thou canſt ſpeed: yet know that Gods gifts are of two ſorts: <hi>Generall,</hi> which are neceſſarie for all the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as Faith, Hope and Charitie: of theſe ſpeak the promiſe, <hi>Ask and ye ſhall have. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> of which there is no promiſe that God will give it to all believers; and ſuch is ſingle life: for otherwiſe we ſhould nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have Church, Common-wealth, nor Family.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> If any ſhall ſay, put caſe I can not obtain ſuch a gift, yet I reſolve againſt marriage: for <hi>Adam</hi> the perfecteſt man, <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt man, and <hi>Sampſon</hi> the ſtrongeſt man were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled by their helpers.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwer, though this reaſon be true (ſince ſin) yet it is not concludent for all ſingle ones. It is better to look before you leap, and to <hi>wed</hi> your prayers to God in Heaven, that he would <hi>wed</hi> you to good wives on earth; for as no worldly comfort is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to a faithfull yokefellow; ſo, woe be to <hi>Sampſon</hi> himſelf if he be married to a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtim.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:169476:13"/>
               <head>SECT. 5.</head>
               <p>BUt to the particulars. Theſe <hi>ſingle perſons</hi> who are Gods timber for a Family, are of foure ſorts,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Old men.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Old women.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Yong men.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Yong women.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Of all theſe I ſhall ſhew you how God frames them by his Word for his building.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Old, or aged men muſt be <hi>Sober, Grave, Temperate, ſound in the Faith, in Charitie, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>in Patience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect: </seg>
                  </label> You will ſay, what need this for them who have one foot in the grave, they are too old to learn a framing now.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> No, no; as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> learned Greeke when he was old, ſo muſt they their duties. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, I write <hi>unto you Fathers</hi> as well as yong men, and babes. This is certain, <hi>He</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 John 2. 13 14: <hi>Aetate major exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> 1 Kings 13</note> 
                  <hi>that is great in age, is greater in example.</hi> The path of hoary hair is more Imitable then that bemired with the mudd of youth. The old Prophet deceived the yong, and brought him to be torn to death by a Lion. This is true alſo, that virtue will make their age to be an <hi>honour</hi> and ornament unto them. An old mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, is as lothſome as a dunghil; an old drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, <note place="margin">Prov. 16. 31</note> as rammiſh as a Bore; an old whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger, as noyſome as hell: but age is a crown of honour, when found in the wayes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169476:14"/> of righteouſneſs. This laſtly is moſt certain, that they have but a ſhort time to live in this world, yong men may die, old men muſt die; therefore old <hi>Alexis</hi> going ſoftly, and ſtoop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, gave this reaſon of it, <hi>I dy by little and little;</hi> and old <hi>Hannah</hi> frequented the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and old <hi>Simeon</hi> waited for the conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paulatim morior.</hi> Luke 2.</note> of Iſrael, that they might be fit for deaths ſtroke when it came.</p>
               <p>If then old men are not too old to learn, let them hearken to Gods framing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They muſt be <hi>Sober,</hi> that is, <hi>moderate</hi> in the uſe of meat and drink. That age is full of coldneſs, weakneſs, drineſs; and therefore doth more deſire to warm, and moyſten it ſelf with meat and drink. In this caſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out godly care, it may miſcarry as we ſee in <hi>Lot,</hi> and <hi>Noah.</hi> Be <hi>Sober,</hi> therefore, ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi> What a ſhame is it for them that have lived ſo long and not to have learned to uſe the creatures aright? How ſhall they be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riſtians,</hi> who for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <note place="margin">Jude.</note> deny their luſts, <hi>but feed without fear?</hi> What an odious thing it is that old men, who ſhould direct others by example, ſhould, by <hi>laying their honour in the duſt,</hi> encourage to ſinne? How lamentable is it to ſee the Image of Gods eternitie (as the <hi>Antient of dayes)</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 7.</note> to be wallowing in the mire of ſins? How would it break a mans ſpirit to think how little time they have to watch (becauſe the <hi>Judge is at the doore,</hi> their ſun is ſetting), and <note place="margin">James 4.</note> yet that they miſpend what they can ſpare in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169476:14"/> ſurfetting? Oh, be not fools in Iſrael, but be <hi>Sober.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt be <hi>Grave,</hi> that is ſeemly, modeſt, and gracious in their carriages. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other age requires other manners.</hi> This may be <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Alia aetas alios mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es poſtulat.</hi> Gen. 23: 6. Gen. 6. 9.</note> preſſed by good patterns and by reaſons. The Patterns are <hi>Abraham,</hi> who for gravitie was accounted <hi>A Prince of God</hi> among the <hi>Hit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites;</hi> and <hi>Henoch,</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> who <hi>walked with God.</hi> For this <hi>Elias</hi> was called <hi>My Father;</hi> and <hi>Maximine</hi> the perſecuting Emperour durſt not look upon <hi>Lucianus</hi> the Martyr, <hi>for fear he ſhould become a Chriſtian.</hi> Yea, <hi>Lacon,</hi> a grave Heathen, being asked, why he wore his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vt eam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuens virum me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſe ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am: &amp; canos intuens ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillos nihil committam illis indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> Levit. 19. 22</note> beard ſo long? Anſwered, <hi>That I, looking upon it, may know my ſelf to be a man; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding my hoary haires may commit nothing unworthy of them.</hi> As to reaſons, God hath highly honoured them, and put upon them the Image of his own Paternitie; and hath therefore provided a Law for them, <hi>Thou ſhalt riſe up before the hoary head.</hi> Yea, out of long experience they are to teach others, and to <hi>be eyes to the blind, feet to the lame.</hi> If they <note place="margin">Job 29. 15. 21.</note> do thus, it will not be accepted except they be <hi>Grave.</hi> Yea let me tell you, old men are eaſily deſpiſed. We know the Proverb, <hi>I adore the Sun riſing, but contemn it ſetting;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Job 29 8. &amp; 30, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> and <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerved all the living with the ſecond child. To prevent this therefore pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretious example of <hi>grave Job.</hi> Could old men deſire zealouſly to hold the crown of age to make their counſel acceptable, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169476:15"/> to keep themſelves from contempt, they would be <hi>Grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt be <hi>Temperate,</hi> that is, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all rebellious luſts of ſinne; as whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, drunkenneſs, luſt, carnal anger, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, Pride, and the like, which moſtly are too properly incident to the vanitie of youth. To be thus is excellent in the Aged, becauſe theſe luſts are abominable in all, much more in the aged. To have eyes full of adulterie, mouthes full of rotten talk, throats the Devils tunnels, is damnable. <hi>Solon</hi> being asked what old age was? Anſwered, it was <hi>the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Vitae hyems.</note> 
                  <hi>winter of life;</hi> and ſhall they bring forth the curſed ſpring of the worſt youth? Beſides, old age ought to be ſet apart for heavenly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, being ready to forſake the earth. It is true that we find ſome old men <hi>whoſe bones are full of the ſinnes of their youth:</hi> Who <note place="margin">Job 21.</note> ſavour as little of this moderate temper, as they whoſe bloud is hotteſt; who, as dregs ſetled in the bottom of the barrel, are as vile as if they were to live over their lives again. But take heed, ſet old <hi>Job</hi> before you, he <note place="margin">Job 1.</note> would give more libertie, then he would take; for while his ſons were abroad in feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he was at home in praying and ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and forget not old <hi>Barzillai,</hi> who would have his ſon taſt of the pleaſures of the <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19. 34, 35, 36. 37.</note> Court, while he would ſtay at home and die.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They muſt be <hi>ſound in the faith.</hi> The three former concerned them as old men, but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169476:15"/> all the next as they are Chriſtian men. This ſoundneſs of faith ſtands in the ſoundneſs of the</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Knowledge of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Deſire after Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Receiving of Chriſt as Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour with confidence.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>And in truth, this is required in old men, Becauſe they have had the uſe of the means longer, and more is required of them that have received much. Yea, they have had longer experience of Gods love in Jeſus Chriſt. Yea, they have the place and <hi>honour of ſpeech</hi> where they come; therefore they <note place="margin">Job 32. 4. Matth. 11.</note> muſt not be <hi>like reeds</hi> ſhaken with the winde, or like chaff carried with every puff. Yea, their bodies and outward man decayeth, therefore they had more need to be ſound in the ſtrength of the inner man. Oh that old men therefore would labour for this, and not be as <hi>Zacharie John Baptiſts</hi> father, or <hi>Sarah,</hi> whoſe ages were means to weaken their faith. Take heed of that (Chriſtians) for this is a ſure note of an heavenly man <hi>to be more flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſ. 40, 30, 31.</note> 
                  <hi>and fruitfull in age; yong men ſhall faint,</hi> and ſtumble, and fall, but <hi>they that wait upon the Lord ſhall renew as the Eagles.</hi> Yea, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſadly that the comfort of old age de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the ſoundneſs of faith. <hi>Dayes are come wherein they have no pleaſure!</hi> but faith <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.</note> ſaith, <hi>Oh forſake me not in my old age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. They muſt be <hi>ſound in Charitie.</hi> As an
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169476:16"/> 
                  <hi>Apple</hi> may be rotten two wayes; In outward appearance, and at the coare! ſo Charitie may be unſound two wayes alſo, when it is ſo <hi>to the outward eye,</hi> by envie, hatred, malice; when it is ſo to the Conſcience of a mans ſelf. Now the godly aged muſt have neither of theſe rotenneſſes, but muſt be ſound in <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, good means</hi> and <hi>good men;</hi> in loving <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 17.</note> them from the heart root, in loving alwayes; For old men in likelyhood are nearer heaven <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note> then yonger, where all are governed by an eternal Law <hi>of Charitie.</hi> If then they would not be outed they muſt be ſound in love; for how ſhall God who is love receive them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heaven who love not?</p>
               <p n="6">6 They muſt be <hi>ſound in Patience.</hi> Oh that they could ſee God in all croſſes, that they could humbly ſubmit to him, that they could reſolve to have a ſhoulder to bear ſo long as God hath an hand to lay on; and that they could as thankfully carrie themſelves to God in the worſt times, as <hi>Iob</hi> did, and wait for <note place="margin">Iob 1.</note> the iſſue. Here were ſound patience indeed, and in truth old men have need of it. For age it ſelf is a ſickneſs, and more inclined to frowardneſs by their infirmities; yea, they muſt be willing to hear Chriſtian advice, when age is readie to ſlip aſide; in both which reſpects they have need to be ſound in patience. As therefore they poſſeſs God in Chriſt by faith, and men by love; ſo them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by patience: and thus are old men ſquared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:169476:16"/>
               <head>SECT. 6.</head>
               <p n="2">2. THe next part of Gods timber for his building are <hi>old women.</hi> Now theſe muſt be <hi>of ſuch behaviovr as becomes holineſs,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>not falſe accuſers, not given to much wine, but teachers of honeſt things to yonger women.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> If you argue, that women need not come to <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 35.</note> the Word to be framed by it, becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let them ask their husbands at home</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> It is but a vain excuſe, for though <hi>Paul</hi> forbids the open and publike ſpeech of women in the Congregations, yet he takes for granted their ſubmitting to Gods Word, without which for want of good husbands, they would be miſerable.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But it may be women are well enough, whether framed yea or no, becauſe they ſhal <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 15.</note> be <hi>ſaved by childbearing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Indeed this were a brave world for them if no childing women ſhould go to hell. All that <hi>Paul</hi> ſignifies is this, that though women have loſt many comforts which they might have had, if ſin had not entered by them, yet <hi>By</hi> or <hi>Thorough</hi> the worſt miſerie of their eſtate here they may be ſaved, if they <hi>continue in Faith, Love, Holineſs, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> You may think happily, that women need not trouble themſelves with the Scripture? becauſe they have other work enough at home.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:169476:17"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> But their beſt work is to know <hi>Chriſt</hi> thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mediatour, out of whom is no ſalvation. Therefore <hi>Solomons</hi> mother requires two things of a virtuous woman, <hi>To overſee the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>wayes of her Family,</hi> and <hi>to open her mouth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wiſedome,</hi> that ſhe may ſhew <hi>the law of Grace</hi> in her lips, that is, the Word of God. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this rule <hi>Timotheus</hi> mother and grandmother taught him the Scripture from his Infanterie: and <hi>Macrina Baſils</hi> nurſe taught him: <hi>Ierome</hi> alſo commendeth <hi>Paula</hi> for teaching her maids the Scriptures: for which end <hi>Caecilia</hi> an honourable <hi>Roman</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, never went without the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> about her; not to mention <hi>Sophia, Sympho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſsa,</hi> and other Martyrs in the Primitive Church.</p>
               <p>And truly, whatſoever may be ſaid, there is great cauſe why women ſhould be ſquared by Gods Word. They are <hi>weaker veſſels,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> is their beſt comfort among their weakneſses. <hi>Women</hi> may have their names <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. Phil. 4. 3. Acts 2. 47.</note> written in <hi>the book of Life,</hi> as well as men; therefore muſt they be <hi>added to the Church,</hi> which muſt be by Knowledge, Faith, and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. Beſides examples of good women in Scripture do preſs them, as <hi>the chief women</hi> of <hi>Theſſolonica, Dorcas, Priſcilla, Mary, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phena,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 17. 4. Acts 18. 26. Rom. 16. 4. 6. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Triphoſa, Perſis,</hi> who believed, were in Chriſt, and lived.</p>
               <p>Weigh therefore how they muſt be framed in particular.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They muſt be in behaviour as becomes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:169476:17"/> ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi> That is, their carriage muſt be ſuch as muſt witneſs the inward ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of their hearts both publikely and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately among themſelves. This muſt be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered foure wayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In countenance,</hi> by expreſſing the inward holineſs of their hearts. When <hi>Eſay</hi> would <note place="margin">Eſ. 3. 16.</note> prove the women of <hi>Sion</hi> to be proud, he doth it by their <hi>countenance,</hi> and when <hi>David</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 130. 1</note> would prove that he had an humble heart, he doth it from his <hi>looks,</hi> ſo ſhall old Matrons do by themſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In geſtures,</hi> when they expreſs the chaſtity of their hearts. The Church is ſaid to have <hi>Doves eyes;</hi> both <hi>beautifull</hi> to allure her own, <note place="margin">Cant.</note> and <hi>terrible</hi> to cruſh the temptations of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In ſpeech,</hi> when it doth expreſs the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, grace and modeſtie of the heart. The faſhion of the <hi>harlot</hi> is to <hi>be babling and loud;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 7. 11.</note> but the modeſt woman keeps her tongue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a bridle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In apparel,</hi> when by the outward ornaments of the body, the inward beautie of the ſoul is ſet forth. The matter of it muſt be meaſured by Abilitie, condition of Life, and Age. The <hi>form</hi> of it muſt not be wanton, ſtrange, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring of lightneſs and ſingularitie, leſt <hi>God viſit them for ſtrange apparel.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Zeph. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>They muſt not be falſe accuſers,</hi> or make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates or Devils; for ſo the word imparteth. This they muſt be carefull to obſerve, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting no falſ things of others, by reporting
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169476:18"/> true things with a charitable mind, by not ſuborning falſ witneſs, or being ſinfully ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent when they ought to maintain Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie. And truely, they had need to watch for this dutie, becauſe their age affords them more familiar acceſs into places, and ſo they may have more occaſion to ſpeak of themſelves and others. Yea, their example would more hurt yonger women, whom they may poyſon, and from whom they may ſteal the vail of modeſtie. Yea, and it would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace their age if they ſhould turn Devils, and blow up like Satans gunpowder, the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of peace where they come. Therefore let them be warie, becauſe <hi>He that deals truely is Gods delight,</hi> and the good name of others <note place="margin">Prov.</note> is next to life.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They muſt <hi>not be given to much wine,</hi> or drink, that is, they muſt take heed of the Bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing diſeaſe, of which too many women are guiltie. The very Heathens did account wine and ſtrong drink diſagreeable to the nature of women; therefore had they <hi>The kiſs of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Oſculum probationis.</note> 
                  <hi>Triall,</hi> by which the kinsfolk tried whether their women friends had been given to wine. Much more muſt Chriſtians be careful, though ſometimes for weakneſs, ſometimes for honeſt comfort; they may uſe that good creature.</p>
               <p>If you ask why old women ſhould be thus? It may be it is, becauſe women of thoſe times had ſuch like meetings, upon womenly oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions as they have now, and the like practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169476:18"/> therefore <hi>Paul</hi> puts a bridle upon them, or becauſe the moderation of old women ſhould be an example unto youger who might eaſily fall into exceſs. Oh therefore that it were thus every where for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of that uſefull, comfortable, and good ſexe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They muſt be <hi>teachers of good things to yonger women.</hi> Though they are not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to teach in publike, yet privately they may among themſelves, as <hi>Paul</hi> warranteth. Every Chriſtian muſt <hi>gather with Chriſt, or elſe they ſcatter:</hi> and all the godly are deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to be ſuch as <hi>whoſe lips feed many,</hi> and <note place="margin">Prov.</note> whoſe <hi>words are health to their bones, and their tongues a tree of Life.</hi> And that women are not excluded we ſee in <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the bleſſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> and <hi>Bathſhebah,</hi> who ſaith, that the <hi>good woman opens her mouth in wiſedome.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 31.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But <hi>what good leſſons</hi> muſt they teach the yonger?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> directeth in termes, That they muſt be <hi>Sober,</hi> not to be Joviall and merrie laſſes; <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 4, 5, 6.</note> That they <hi>love their husbands;</hi> not to be idle, wanton and careleſs which end in the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goes forward; That they be Diſcreet, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcern what is good for their husbands and Families; That they be Chaſte; not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſt in Word, Geſture, Attire, but <hi>drink</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov.</note> 
                  <hi>water out of their own ciſtern;</hi> That they be keepers at home; not gadders from houſe to houſe to carrie news; That they be good, not to ſuffer their hearts to ſwell with pride, or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169476:19"/> their tongues with ſcolding, ſlanders, or oathes; That they be <hi>obedient to their Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,</hi> not to ſtrive for maſterie, and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to yield, either by flatterie, or braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Oh, want of theſe leſsons by the aged, and want of learning them by yonger wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men hath made this good ſex to be deſpiſed by Heathens.</p>
               <p>Hence <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> beholding a little wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <note place="margin">Parum pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrum mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num malum. Ille inducit quales eſſe deberent: Ego vero, quales ſunt.</note> faire, ſaid, Behold a <hi>little beautifull Creature, but a great miſchief</hi> in an houſe; and <hi>Philoxenas</hi> being asked why he ſtill ſpake of wicked women, when <hi>Sophocles</hi> ſpake of good ones? Anſwered; <hi>He ſpeaks of ſuch as they ought to be, but I, of ſuch as they are.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem therefore the honour of your ſexe, and let old women be ſuch, and teach ſo as aged <hi>Paul</hi> would have them,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 7.</head>
               <p>THe third, and fourth part of Gods tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to be framed, are <hi>yong men,</hi> and <hi>yong women.</hi> Theſe have a threefold dutie put upon them.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>To rememher their Creatour in the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 1 Tit. 2. 6. 2 Tim. 2. 22 Levit. 19. 32.</note> 
                     <hi>dayes of their youth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>To be ſoberminded, and to fly the luſts of youth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>To honour the perſons of the Aged.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>They muſt certainly learn their duties as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169476:19"/> well as others, for <hi>Titus</hi> was given in charge <note place="margin">Tit: 2. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>to exhort yong men;</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> doth it, and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> muſt feed Chriſts Lambs, as well as his Sheep. Yea, the word is directed to them <note place="margin">1 John 2. 13. Pſalm 119. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>by name</hi> as well as others to <hi>redreſs</hi> their wayes by, and ſinne faſtned upon them doth moſt harm, as a blaſt in the Spring doth hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fruit in Autumne.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They muſt <hi>remember their Creator in the dayes of their youth;</hi> that is, conſecrate their firſt years to the knowledge and ſervice of God. He that ſails a long voyage muſt not ſleep while the wind ſerves, and the ſhip is ſtrong. As <hi>Abraham</hi> roſe early to ſacrifice <note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> yong <hi>Iſaac:</hi> ſo muſt yong people begin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to mortifie their ſins. God loves infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely <note place="margin">Dan. 1. 4.</note> more then the King of <hi>Babel</hi> to have <hi>yong men</hi> and well favoured to be choſen to ſtand in his Court. Their ſervice is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: but to ſerve God when they can ſerve ſinne no longer is not thankworthie. It is very hard to turn back after the wildneſſe of that age by repentance. The curſe of God frownes upon them, <hi>VVoe to him that hath a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>male in his flock, and offers a corrupt thing.</hi> The further they run after the courſ of the world, the harder will their journey be at the latter end. Therefore they muſt take time while time ſerves, and ſtrike while the iron is hot. What though ſome old men give them bad patterns? Let yong <hi>Shem</hi> be ſober, though old <hi>Noah</hi> be overtaken with wine. Let yong <hi>Ioſeph</hi> be chaſte, though old <hi>Lot</hi> fall into the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169476:20"/> pit of Inceſt, Let yong <hi>Samuel</hi> be faithful, though old <hi>Eli</hi> be indulgent. Let yong <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> be ſincere, though old <hi>Saul</hi> be an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite. Though Iſrael play the harlot, yet let not <hi>Iudah</hi> ſinne: and though old men fail and fall, let yong people ſtand and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. They have excellent yong men to be their patterns, as <hi>Daniel, Ioſeph, Samuel, Ioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, Timothy:</hi> and this they muſt know, that the ſinnes of youth wound deeply. <hi>David</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm 25.</note> cries out, <hi>Remember not the ſinnes of my youth;</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> was in pitiful plight when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, <hi>Thou writeſt bitter things againſt me,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Job.</note> 
                  <hi>and makeſt me poſſeſſe the ſinnes of my youth,</hi> theſe have hard teeth; and wound deep.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt be <hi>ſober minded,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus,</hi> which he expounds to <hi>Timothy</hi> by <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 6. 2 Tim. 2. 22</note> 
                  <hi>flying the luſts of youth.</hi> Sobrietie is a grace that moderates affections, and luſts in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral: and is fitly required of yong perſons, ſeeing their ſinnes lye in the ill managing of the ſtrength of luſts. They carrie <hi>wrath, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation</hi> and <hi>envie</hi> in their hearts. They are <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11. 10.</note> full of pride and preſumption, as he vthat ſaid to Chriſt. <hi>All theſe have I kept from my youth,</hi> when he had not kept one. They are <hi>inconſiderate,</hi> as that yong fool, who was led by the harlot as <hi>an Ox to the ſlaughter</hi> They <note place="margin">Prov. 7.</note> ſwell with raſhneſſe, as <hi>Rehoboams</hi> green Counſellers. Indeed that age is like a ſeething pot which caſts out ſcum. Therefore God mocks them, <hi>Reioyce O yong man in thy youth;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.</note> but <hi>remember thou ſhalt come to judgement;</hi> and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169476:20"/> warns them ſadly to be ſober, and to flie the luſts of youth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They muſt <hi>honour the perſons of the aged.</hi> Old men are Fathers, and old age is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in it ſelf; therefore it ſhould be reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced, by riſing up before them, by being ſilent before them as <hi>Elihu,</hi> and by ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <note place="margin">Job 32. 4, 6.</note> to them with a <hi>ſubmiſſion of reverence.</hi> Thus is Gods timber framed, and made fit for Gods building in a Family.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 8.</head>
               <p n="2">2. VVE now come to the ſetting up of this building of God. And becauſe every houſe conſiſts of a <hi>Foundation,</hi> and an <hi>upper building,</hi> this muſt have both.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Foundation</hi> is <hi>Marriage in the Lord:</hi> about which conſider two things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>VVhat Marriage in the Lord is?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>How it mny be ſo undertaken, as it may be a good Foundation of Gods building?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Marriage</hi> in the Lord is <hi>a Covenant of God, whereby all ſorts of fit couples, may of two be made one fleſh, to multiply an holy ſeed, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void fornication, and mutually to comfort each other.</hi> It is a <hi>Covenant of God;</hi> ſo God calls it, when he ſaith of a looſe woman, <hi>She forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 2. 17. 1 Cor. 7. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>the Covenant of her God.</hi> It is for all <hi>fit cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples:</hi> fit I ſay, becauſe not for men and men,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169476:21"/> women and women, men and beaſts, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Infidels: for we muſt not be <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally yoked.</hi> Theſe fit perſons may of two <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. Gen. 2. 23, 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mal. 2. 15. 1 Cor. 7. 2. Gen. 24. 67 Ruth 3. 1.</note> be made <hi>one fleſh,</hi> to multiply an <hi>holy ſeed,</hi> to <hi>avoid fornication;</hi> and <hi>mutually to comfort</hi> each other, when the husband is <hi>a reſt</hi> for his wife. But to take it up more fully, weigh,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>From whence it muſt be ſought?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Who may ſeek it?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>How many may make the ſame Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant at once?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. It muſt be ſought <hi>from God,</hi> whoſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant it is. Therefore <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant, <note place="margin">Gen. 24. 12 60. Gen. 28. 2, 3.</note> and <hi>Rebekahs</hi> friends prayed, and when <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> was ſent to <hi>Padan Aram</hi> upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, it was with a ſolemn eye to God. Truly, <hi>no good ſucceſſe</hi> can be expected but <note place="margin">Jam. 1. 17.</note> from God; and this is the way to comfort againſt all troubles in the wedded eſtate; yet I doubt we may ſay as <hi>Laban</hi> to <hi>Iacob</hi> in another caſe, <hi>it is not the manner of this place.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 29. 26.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It may be ſought <hi>of all ſorts of perſons</hi> without exception. The Apoſtles <hi>(In all)</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 4.</note> doth include both things, and perſons. And verily, it is honourable in all, in reſpect of the <hi>Author,</hi> God; the <hi>Time,</hi> Innocencie; the <hi>Place,</hi> Paradiſe, and the uſe and <hi>office,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the Church. I know that Papiſts ſay otherwiſe, and make it a means to advance the Doctrine of <hi>Daemons:</hi> but it is but <hi>groſs hypocriſie</hi> to pretend Chaſtitie for a cover of whoredome: <hi>Preſumptuous pride</hi> to offer at
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169476:21"/> greater perfection then was in Paradiſe, and <hi>humane Policy,</hi> to keep wealth together to mate the greateſt Princes and kingdoms.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Though all ſorts may ſeek it, yet two onely at once may be <hi>made one fleſh.</hi> Hence is it that <hi>Polygamy</hi> was ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Levit. 18. 18. Matth. 19. 6 Eph. 5. 31.</note> God his Inſtitution. I know that three things may be ſaid to juſtifie it; the example of the <hi>Patriarks,</hi> the ſpeech of <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>God's Law,</hi> but all three will be found too weak. As to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the <hi>Patriarks,</hi> conſider the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, the Event, the Ground of their having many wives.</p>
               <p>The Originall was in wicked <hi>Lamech,</hi> who firſt ſpake this language, <hi>Heare yee wives of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Lamech:</hi> and this is of no credit or comfort. The event was never comfortable to Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, as ye may ſee in <hi>Lamechs, Abrahams, Iacobs,</hi> and <hi>Elkanah's.</hi> The ground was miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding of the promiſed ſeeds multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, which might be conceived not to be made good without many wives. This it pleaſed God to paſs over as the fruit of their ignorance, eſpecially it carrying puniſhment in the mouth of it, to make them and us wiſer.</p>
               <p>As to the ſpeech of <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>David, God</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>gave thee thy lords wives into thy boſome,</hi> it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to convince <hi>David,</hi> that God gave them under his hand, government and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: or that God permitted him to take Livery and ſeiſin of his Kingdome according
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169476:22"/> to the guiſe of that time, which was by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the wives and concubines of his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours. This was the reaſon, that <hi>Adoniah</hi> deſired <hi>Abiſhag,</hi> and <hi>Abſalon</hi> went in unto his fathers concubines. All this comes far ſhort of proving lawfulneſs. As to that <hi>Law,</hi> in <note place="margin">Deut. 21. 15, 16.</note> which God takes order for one that had two wives, and children by them; God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it not to be done, but when it was done, he provided a law to prevent the greateſt confuſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How <hi>marriage may be ſo undertaken as it may be in the Lord to us?</hi> By going along with God,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>In the Antecedents.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>In the Concomitants.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>In the Conſequents of it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Antecedents</hi> of an holy marriage are, A right choice by the right marks. As for a right choice,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>You muſt not chooſe within the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees prohibited.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>You muſt look more to inward good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs then to outward goods.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Degrees prohibited,</hi> wherein you <note place="margin">Levit. 18. 6, 7. &amp;c.</note> may not chuſe are ſet down in the Law. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> If you ſay, theſe are <hi>Levitical,</hi> and do not bind us. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> That is not ſo; for the <hi>Canaanites</hi> (who were not tied to <hi>Levitical</hi> Lawes) were <hi>rooted out</hi> for not obſerving them. And <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 3. 24, 25.</note> urged the ſame Law in the New Teſtament
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169476:22"/> againſt <hi>Herod;</hi> yea, and Nature it ſelf hath <note place="margin">Mark 6. 18.</note> abhorred ſuch conjunctions, which have been prohibited by Heathens.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> You will ſay, <hi>Adams</hi> ſonnes married with their ſiſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> True, but that could not be avoyded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out another creation, when God had once given a Law of multiplication: but yet that was repealed by God afterwards to which we muſt ſtick.</p>
               <p>If ye ſay, that after that time <hi>Abraham</hi> married <hi>Sarah,</hi> whow he calls <hi>his ſiſter.</hi> True, <note place="margin">Gen. 20. 12</note> but <hi>ſiſter</hi> was a name common to kindred of that ſexe, and theſe that were brought up in the Family, as <hi>Sarah</hi> was in <hi>Abrahams</hi> fathers houſe, and this is without doubt, that God tolerated many things then which he did not approve, which the learned call <hi>toleration without approbation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But ſay you, Is it not plainly ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not diſcover the ſhame of thy brothers wife?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Levit. 18. 16. Deut. 25. 5. Rom. 8.</note> and yet again, if the <hi>brother</hi> died without iſſue, <hi>the brother</hi> raiſed up ſeed unto him; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> true, but that was a ſpecial exception from the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral rule, for the honour of Jeſus Chriſt (as the <hi>firſt-born</hi> among many brethren) whom we muſt honour by bringing forth fruit unto him: To teach us that that law was in the Jewiſh pedagogie as proper to them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In choice, <hi>you muſt more looke to inward goodneſs,</hi> then to outward goods. The neglect of this was one prime cauſe of deſtroying the <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 2, 3. Gen. 24. 3.</note> old world, which made <hi>Abraham</hi> warie in a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169476:23"/> match for his ſon, and of our good God's gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a charge that we <hi>be not unequally</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 614. Neh. 13. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>yoked</hi> to the <hi>hinderance of Religion.</hi> Muſt we not follow our Bridegroome <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who in the <note place="margin">Pſalm 50.</note> choice of his Spouſe looks not to outward priviledges?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> No, ſay you, nor to inward graces nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For he marrieth us when we have no beautie.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> It is true, becauſe he can make good, that he may marry good. <hi>Moſes</hi> marries an <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopian,</hi> and connot change either her colour or her qualities; but Chriſt makes us beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full with <hi>the beautie that he puts upon us.</hi> Muſt <note place="margin">Ezek. 16.</note> we not, laſtly, look to that which in true judgement is to be valued above all? What can this be in man or woman but <hi>goodneſſe.</hi> It is better with <hi>Boaz</hi> to take <hi>Ruth</hi> from among the gleaners, and with <hi>Jacob</hi> to ſerve ſeven years for a wench that keepeth ſheep, then to have an Idolatrous <hi>Maacah,</hi> a treacherous <hi>Athaliah,</hi> a painted <hi>Iezabel,</hi> or a vexing <hi>Zip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porah</hi> with great revenues. Yet I pray, what are the queſtions now? what portion? what joynture? what money in hand? what ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the reſt? Not a word, how religious? how vertuous? wanton <hi>Dinah,</hi> ſubtle <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah,</hi> ſcorning <hi>Michal,</hi> ſullen <hi>Vaſhti</hi> may paſs upon theſe terms. But were ſhe as obedient as <hi>Sarah,</hi> as wiſe as <hi>Deborah,</hi> as religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> as devout as <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi> as well affected to the Word as <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> if ſhe bring nothing but goodneſſe,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169476:23"/> ſhe may ſtand at doore and coole her feet.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> You will ask whether a man may have no reſpect to outward things? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Yes ſurely upon two grounds. It is fit, as for age, ſo for ſtate, and means there ſhould be a proportion; for <hi>God is not the Author of confuſion;</hi> therefore <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>David</hi> was not apt to entertain the motion of marrying with a Kings daughter when ſhe was offered, being himſelf but the ſonne of <hi>Iſhi:</hi> Beſides, this rule in Scripture, <hi>Parents</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>lay up for their children,</hi> bindeth to care to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them ſo, that they may enjoy that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thing, to give rather then to receive. Yet take this in, that it muſt not be the chief thing in choice. Though <hi>Agar</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> may dwell together, yet <hi>Sarah</hi> muſt be miſtreſs; ſo muſt <hi>goodneſs</hi> be predominant above <hi>goods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now ſecondly, What are the right marks which muſt regulate our choiſe in husbands and wives? There are five ſorts of marriages: A marriage of <hi>Honour,</hi> when Chriſt and his Church make one myſticall body. A marriage of <hi>Labour,</hi> when men pull wives to them by the fingers, not by the ears, and do marry portions, not wives. A mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of <hi>Lust,</hi> when the eye is party, Parent, Preacher, all in all, as in <hi>Sampſons.</hi> A mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of <hi>Grief,</hi> when wicked perſons meet, of whom is that Proverb, Better one houſe filled, then two ſpilled. A marriage of <hi>Love,</hi> when Chriſtian godly ones are linked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and this comes on, and is concluded upon right choice.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:169476:24"/> 1. By <hi>report,</hi> what fame ſhe hath among the godly. A good man and woman dwell at the ſign of a good name. 2. By <hi>looks,</hi> Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <note place="margin">Prov. 17. 24 Eſ. 3. 9.</note> is in the face of him that hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. This is like the gate of the Temple which is called Beautiful. 3. By <hi>talking</hi> and <hi>ſilence;</hi> ſuch as a man or woman is, ſuch is their talk. Talk in a woman muſt be ſparing; Silence is her beſt Ornament. She that is full of words, is not likely to prove either <hi>quiet,</hi> becauſe <hi>alwaies babling:</hi> Or <hi>wiſe,</hi> for by thy <note place="margin">Prov. 7.</note> words thou ſhalt be juſtified to be wiſe, or to be otherwiſe. 4. By <hi>apparel,</hi> this is the Ivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh of the mind. As the modeſt woman is known by her apparel, anſwerable to her birth, and breeding; ſo the immodeſt by her whoriſh attire, as we ſee in <hi>Tamar.</hi> 5. By <note place="margin">Gen. 38. 14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>company,</hi> fellows in nature and ſinne will be fellows in league, as <hi>Rehoboam</hi> and his yong counſellers; therefore <hi>David,</hi> when he was good, ſaid, <hi>Away from me ye wicked,</hi> I will <note place="margin">Pſalm 119.</note> keep the Commandements of my God. 6. By <hi>education,</hi> whether they have continued in vertuous breeding. <hi>Judas</hi> may be with the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> for his own turn, but continues not. Let theſe marks be well applied to every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and theſe anſwerably made, and the wedding garment ſhall not be made of linſey wolſey, nor the marriage ground ploughed with an Oxe and an Aſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:169476:24"/>
               <head>SECT: 9.</head>
               <p n="2">2. THe <hi>Concomitants</hi> with marriage in the Lord are three,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The gift of the Parents.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The bleſſing of the Miniſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The mutual rejoycing of the friends.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Gift of the Parents</hi> either expreſly, or tacitely, (or of thoſe who are <hi>in place of Parents)</hi> crowns the wedding with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. For marriage is not onely a <hi>Civil,</hi> but <note place="margin">Matth. 19.</note> a <hi>Divine</hi> conjunction, therefore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>thoſe whom God hath joyned together.</hi> God doth <note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> it not now Immediately, as he joyned <hi>Adam,</hi> and <hi>Evah,</hi> but by the Parental prerogative: Therefore, ſaith God, <hi>Take ye wives to your</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 29. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>ſons, and give your daughters in marriage.</hi> Yea, the light of Nature teacheth us thus much; for let a Son privily alienate his Fathers land; ask nature, whether this be good? She cries out of every natural mouth; No, becauſe the land is not the Sons, but the <hi>Fathers goods.</hi> So is it in this caſe, becauſe children are part <hi>of the Fathers goods.</hi> Hence when Satan had power to ſpoil <hi>Iobs goods</hi> he ſlew his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: <note place="margin">Job 1. Exod. 21. 7. <hi>Non ut<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viant, ſed ut ducantur, ut Rabbi.</hi>
                  </note> and the Jews had power <hi>to ſell their children, not for vaſsalage and ſervice, but for mariage.</hi> If then children ſhall go againſt their conſents in this, it will breed a pricking at the latter end.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The next thing in marriage is <hi>the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:169476:25"/> 
                  <hi>of the Miniſter,</hi> that is, commending them being contracted, and their ſtate to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God. For when God had joyned our firſt Parents, he ſaid, <hi>Encreaſe and multiply:</hi> ſo the Miniſter in Gods room may pray this <note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> to be given. Yea, marriage is the Seminarie of the Church, therefore cannot be better ſet on, then by the ſolemneſt Prayers. I do not ſay, that marriage can not be without them; but I am ſure that this is agreeable to that rule of <hi>Paul, Let all things be done in order.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 40. Gen. 29. 22. John 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>mutual rejoycing of the friends</hi> comes in next; and ſurely there is a lawfulneſſe of feaſting, and mutual rejoycing at marriages. Elſe Chriſt would not have bleſſed one with his preſence and firſt miracle; nor would <note place="margin">Eſ. 62. 5.</note> God have deſcribed the joy that he takes in <note place="margin">Matth. 9. 15 Matth. 22.</note> his Church by the <hi>joy of marriage;</hi> nor would Chriſt have compared the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to a wedding <hi>feaſt.</hi> But let me ſay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that there are no greater ſins committed then about things lawfull.</p>
               <p>It is lawfull to <hi>eat, drink, weare apparel,</hi> and to <hi>feaſt;</hi> hence thouſands of exceſſes, and miſeries have come in. <hi>Exceſſes,</hi> as at <hi>Nabals</hi> feaſt, was drunkenneſſe: at <hi>Abſolons,</hi> was murther, at <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> his, was a breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and his wife <hi>Vaſhti;</hi> at <hi>Belteſhaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> carrouſing and blaſphemy, at <hi>Herods,</hi> wanton dancing, and cutting off of <hi>Iohn Baptists</hi> head. <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ries,</hi> as <hi>Elah</hi> was ſmote and killed while he was drinking: <hi>Benhadad</hi> was ſurpriſed: <hi>Iſrael,</hi> while meat was in their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169476:25"/> mouth, felt wrath; and <hi>Jobs</hi> children were ſtifled. Therefore warily conſider what ye do at weddings, and what ye ſhould do. <hi>Ye do rejoyce</hi> indeed, but it is with wanton dancings, bawdy jeſts, and helliſh carrowſings. But what ſhould ye do? Ye ſhould be carefull to prevent exceſs, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Take heed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luke 21.</note> 
                  <hi>that your hearts be not oppreſſed with ſurfetting and drunkenneſs, leſt that day come upon you at unawares.</hi> Ye ſhould bring God into all your thoughts, that you <hi>feed not without fear.</hi> Ye <note place="margin">Iude. Philip. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> ſhould do nothing which is diſhoneſt, or <hi>of ill report.</hi> Ye ſhould have good wiſhes, ſpeaches, counſels, and prayers to the new married couples, like thoſe that ſaid, <hi>The</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ruth 4. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord make thy wife like Rachel and Leah, which two builded the houſe of Iſrael, and do thou wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily in Ephrata, and be famous in Bethlehem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 10.</head>
               <p n="3">3. THe conſequents of marriage in the Lord are two,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Cohabitation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Communion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Man and wife <hi>muſt dwell together.</hi> Let the husband <hi>dwell with his wife,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 7. Prov. 5. 18, 19.</note> and <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rejoyce in the wife of thy youth, and let her breaſts ſatisfie thee at all times, and delight continually in her.</hi> This cannot be without Cohabitation. The firſt inſtitution
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169476:26"/> was a remedy againſt ſolitarineſs, <hi>It is not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>good for man to be alone, let us make an help meet for him,</hi> and <hi>let him cleave to his wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> I know what you will ſay; may they never live aſunder?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Yes, upon three occaſions; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon mutual conſent</hi> for a time for the good of the Family. <hi>My husband</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>is not at home, he is gone</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 7. 19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>a far journey, at the time appointed he will come again. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon Compulſion,</hi> when perſecution, or impriſonment forceth it. When ſome weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie affairs either in Church, or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth requires it. This was <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riahs</hi> caſe <note place="margin">2 Sam. 11. 11.</note> when he would not go to his own houſe while the <hi>Ark,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> with his <hi>Lord Ioab</hi> were in Tents. Yet muſt they not live aſunder out of choice. It is for an harlot to be called a <hi>ſtrange woman,</hi> but for a <note place="margin">Prov. 2. 16. 2 Sam. 12.</note> wife to be <hi>a lamb in the boſome,</hi> as for the other cauſes, ſo for ſameneſſe of dwelling.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As <hi>Cohabitation</hi> followes upon marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 3. 1 Cor. 7. 4.</note> ſo <hi>Communion,</hi> which ſtands in three things; a <hi>communion of Bodies,</hi> a <hi>communio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of helps,</hi> and a <hi>communion of joyes.</hi> They muſt have a <hi>communion of Bodies,</hi> whereby they <hi>defraud not one another, except it be by conſent for a time, that they may give themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> faſting and prayer,</hi> yet muſt not this be exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive: for there may be too much uxorious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at home, as well as adulterie abroad <note place="margin">Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k. 18. 6. 1 Cor. 7. 5. Gen. 25. 21 1 Sam. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note> And it muſt be <hi>ſanctified</hi> by the Word o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, and Prayer. Doe it <hi>by rule,</hi> and <hi>with Prayer,</hi> as <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Hannah</hi> did. They muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:169476:26"/> have a <hi>Communion of helps,</hi> in nouriſhing, and cheriſhing each other. To this end there muſt be a <hi>communion of goods;</hi> they muſt have one purſe, but not for waſte: a communion of <hi>Counſel</hi> in matters domeſtical; they muſt have one head, as <hi>Pilats</hi> wife and the <hi>Shuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite,</hi> and a communion of <hi>labours;</hi> they muſt have one hand, and that an helper.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, they muſt have a <hi>communion of joy,</hi> by having one heart, as <hi>Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Rebeckah,</hi> who ſported together, and as <hi>Solomon</hi> gives <note place="margin">Gen. 26. 8. Prov. 5. 18, 19.</note> in rule; <hi>Rejoyce with the wife of thy youth.</hi> Oh how happy a foundation of Gods building would ſuch a marriage lay, to laſt till death us do part.</p>
               <p>Thus of the firſt part of Gods ſetting up of his building in a Family, <hi>the Foundation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 11.</head>
               <p>NOw ſecondly, of the upper building, which ſtands perfectly,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>In wife, and husband.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>In parents and children.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>In maſters and ſervants.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Begin where God begins, ſtill with infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours. <note place="margin">Amor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendit, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> Love deſcends, but dutie aſcends. The firſt pair of <hi>beams</hi> in an houſe builded by God are <hi>wife</hi> and <hi>husband,</hi> who bear up this frame. <hi>The wife muſt ſubmit to her husband as unto the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 22, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord;</hi> yea, as <hi>the Church is ſubject to Chriſt.</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:169476:27"/> The woman (ſaith <hi>Paul)</hi> is <hi>bound to the law</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 2</note> 
                  <hi>of her husband;</hi> yea, <hi>this is comely;</hi> it is the beſt faſhion that ever they wore. Therefore <note place="margin">Col. 3. 18. 1 Tim. 2. 12.</note> (ſaith God) <hi>I permit not a woman to uſurp au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Whatſoever thou permitteſt will ſome women ſay, I will do it. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Nay, ſaith God, <hi>Thy deſire ſhall be ſubiect to thy husband, and he ſhall rule over thee.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> Will any good woman ask me, <hi>What it is to ſubmit,</hi> that ſhe may conſcionably do it? </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> It is to put her ſelf willingly under the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of her husband. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> Will ſhe further ask me how ſhe muſt ſubmit? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Surely, not by way of bondage, but free ſervice for her ſelf; becauſe ſhe and her husband do make but one. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> Will ſhe further ask wherein ſhe muſt ſubmit? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>In all things,</hi> that are lawfull, and honeſt. <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 22.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In general, ſhe muſt ſubmit to her husbands <hi>honour. Sarah</hi> honoured her husband, and <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him Lord.</hi> The good wife calls her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 6. Hoſ. 2. Prov. 7. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſhi,</hi> my man; but the harlot ſaith plain <hi>Iſh,</hi> the man is gone abroad; this is a clear ſign that ſhe honours him not.</p>
               <p>In particular, ſhe muſt ſubmit three wayes. By an <hi>inward act of the mind,</hi> acknowledging <note place="margin">Eph. 5. ult.</note> his <hi>headſhip,</hi> and taking direction from him, if he be wiſe, and for him, if he be a fool. By an inward act of the will conforming to his good manners and affections. By theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward acts of dutie which depend upon theſe thus;</p>
               <p n="1">1. They muſt anſwer their husbands wills.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169476:27"/> Their queſtions muſt not be, Whoſe will ſhall be done: for God ſaith, <hi>Thy deſires ſhal</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>be ſubject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But what if the wils of their husbands be wicked.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Then whether it be better to obey God or him judge you. But in all domeſticall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, as the Moon doth vail at the preſence of the Sun, ſo muſt the wife at the preſence of her husband.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt anſwer their husbands <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings 4. 22. Gen. 16. 6.</note> as the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> who took directions from their husbands.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But ſhall not the wife imploy her know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and diſcretion for the good of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Yes, yet with ſubmiſſion to him as head. As when two ſtrings are ſtroke upon a Lute, the ſound is attributed to the lowdeſt: ſo muſt the wife take and uſe direction to the honour of her husband.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But you will ſay, ſome wives are wiſer then their husbands.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> In truth ſo moſt of them are unhappie to think, and ſometimes it is true; yet the beſt part of their wiſdome is imployed in uſing it for their Husbands honour, and not her own alone, to diſgrace her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> No? did not <hi>Abigail</hi> call her husband fool? and why may not others alſo? <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 25.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> It was well known he was a fool; for from thence he had his name <hi>Nabal.</hi> She reveals
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169476:28"/> no ſecret, but ſpeaks of that which was in every bodies mouth. Beſides, it was not to his face to ſtir up ſtrife; nor behind his back to diſgrace him, but it was to ſave his life. As Chirurgions to ſave the body will cut off a limb, ſo ſhe was willing to blur his well known name to ſave his life.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They muſt anſwer their husbands na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural diſpoſitions which are without ſinne. So <hi>Rebeckah</hi> provided ſavoury meat forher <note place="margin">Gen.</note> old husband, ſuch as he loved: as a looking glaſs ſhe ſhewed the countenance of her husbands nature as it was.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They muſt anſwer their husbands ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual endowments, by kindling, not cooling graces which are given for the family. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe muſt read and pray with him, and for him, and hear his advices, and be a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter comfort then <hi>Jobs</hi> wife was to him in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie.</p>
               <p>I remember a ſad ſtorie upon mine own <note place="margin">Note.</note> knowledge <hi>An honeſt Chriſtian man</hi> had a wife, worldly, and diſtruſtfull; and he being much in good exerciſes, morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Family, ſhe would diſturb him, and go about ratling her keyes, or making ſome other noiſe to hinder him, pretending that his time ſpent that way might be imployed in getting money for his Family.</p>
               <p>This woman was given over by God to the Devils temptations ſo far, that ſhe thruſt a knife into the pit of her ſtomach and killed her ſelf; yet before ſhe died, ſhe confeſſed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169476:28"/> thus much to me, and craved Gods pardon as well as ſhe could. Oh had it not been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ſhe and her husband had walked hand in hand to heaven with her due ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> If now, Fourthly, the good wife will ask me why ſhe muſt ſubmit?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Surely the reaſons are invincible, <hi>The order of Creation</hi> requires it: <hi>Adam</hi> was firſt created, next <hi>Evah</hi> for him: ſo the wife is for <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 8 1 Tim. 2. 14.</note> the husband, as her head. <hi>The order of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion</hi> requires it. <hi>The woman was firſt in the tranſgreſſion.</hi> She was firſt in evil, laſt in good; therefore ſhe muſt ſubmit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The union</hi> betwixt man and wife requires it. <note place="margin">Eph. 5.</note> The husband is the <hi>head</hi> of the wife, for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, protection, and influence. The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>gives not the name</hi> to the husband, but <note place="margin">Eſ. 4. 1. Gen. 2.</note> the husband to the wife; and to impoſe a name is a ſign of Soveraigntie.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Evah</hi> was called <hi>Iſha,</hi> of <hi>Iſh:</hi> and <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> wife was called the <hi>Shulamite,</hi> and the <note place="margin">Quando ego ero Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us, tu cris Caia.</note> 
                  <hi>Roman</hi> ſaid to his wife, <hi>when I ſhall be Caius, Thou ſhalt be my Caia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore let all good wives learn this comely leſſon to ſubmit. There are foure enemies in ſome womens breaſts unto this. <hi>Want of wit,</hi> to know their place; <hi>Want of love,</hi> becauſe they married not in the Lord; <hi>Pride,</hi> in aſpiring to maſterſhip; and <hi>love of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities</hi> of this world, againſt the minds of their husbands. But pray for maſtery over theſe, and ſubmit.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:169476:29"/>
               <p> Be warie of offending your Husbands; Doe as <hi>their hearts may reſt in you;</hi> and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <note place="margin">Prov. 31.</note> all for the honour, and profit of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But ſaith the good wife, <hi>May I not diſpoſe of any of my husbands goods?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I reade three caſes in which they may; Where it tends <hi>to keep from ſinne,</hi> and to preſerve their Husbands life: This was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigails</hi> caſe: Where the <hi>Husband is fooliſh,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 18.</note> and ſees not what is good for himſelf and his Family; this alſo was <hi>Abigails</hi> caſe.</p>
               <p>Where the Husband is an enemy to Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Mercie, and will ſuffer nothing to be done, either by way of Honorarie, or reliefe: this was <hi>Iohanna</hi> the wife of <hi>Chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa's</hi> caſe. <note place="margin">Luke 8. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Yet muſt it be to honour her Husband, not her ſelf: and ſo frugally, and wiſely, that the Husbands houſe want nothing to further credit or comfort.</p>
               <closer>Do thus and proſper.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:169476:29"/>
               <head>SECT. 12.</head>
               <p>THe husband is next, who muſt <hi>honour his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>wife as the weaker veſſel.</hi> There is a double honour; Of <hi>Subiection,</hi> ſo the wife muſt honour her husband: Of <hi>Love</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placence, ſo the husband muſt honour his wife. This honour ſtands in <hi>Love,</hi> and in the <note place="margin">Velle cuique quod bonum eſt.</note> fruits of it. His love to her muſt be a dear comforting love; not ordinary, which is to will to every one that which is good, but by which they are glued one unto another to do good, and not ill unto one another all the dayes of their lives. The fruits of it are theſe that follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He muſt account her his <hi>yoak-fellow,</hi> ſtanding on even ground though drawing on the left ſide.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He muſt dwell with her, that he may be <note place="margin">Ruth 4. 11. Ruth 3. 1. Prov. 5. 18, 19.</note> a <hi>reſt</hi> for her, as for his own Vine, that ſhe may proſper.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He muſt <hi>dwell cheerfully</hi> with her, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> with his beloved <hi>Rebeckah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. He muſt <hi>direct</hi> her, and be the <hi>guide of her youth,</hi> both in civil things, as <hi>Abraham</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 2. 17. Gen. 20. 16.</note> directed <hi>Sarah</hi> when he entertained his ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; and in ſpirituals, as when the <hi>Shuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> husband directed her.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He muſt protect her and be the <hi>covering of her eyes,</hi> and <hi>ſpread the skirt</hi> of his garment over her; that is, provide for her, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect <note place="margin">Ruth 3. 9. 1 Sam. 30. 5, 6.</note> her, as <hi>David</hi> did his wife, when ſhe was taken by the <hi>Amalekites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:169476:30"/> 6. He muſt <hi>provide</hi> neceſſaries for her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to, but not above, his means, as God ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not diminiſh her food, rayment,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 21. 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>and the recompence of her virginitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. He muſt <hi>bear with her infirmities:</hi> not <hi>ſinnefull,</hi> theſe muſt be cured by inſtruction, reproof, prayer,; but <hi>paſsionall,</hi> as grief, fear, diſtruſt; and <hi>Penal,</hi> as <hi>Jacob</hi> did bear with <hi>Leahs</hi> blear eyes, and <hi>Rachels</hi> barrenneſs, and <hi>Elkanah,</hi> who would not love <hi>Hannah</hi> the worſ for a fault ſhe could not help.</p>
               <p n="8">8. He muſt ſuffer himſelf in ſome things to be adviſed by her. This will comfort them <note place="margin">Gen. 21. 12 1 Sam. 1. 23</note> againſt thoſe things they ſuffer in their husbands love. This will encourage them to undergo joynt care in the Family.</p>
               <p n="9">9. He muſt <hi>not be bitter unto her;</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> wherein <note place="margin">Col. 3. 19.</note> doth that ſtand? </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Not in croſſing her in worldly, wicked, and want on things; nor in a juſt reproving her folly, but it ſtands in Affections, words, and deeds. In <hi>affections,</hi> when trifles draw the heart from love to ſowre hatred. In <hi>words,</hi> when their tender natures are unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wounded by them. In <hi>deeds,</hi> when the wife is uſed like a drudge more like, then like a wife; as when ſhe is deprived of houſhold government, when ſhe is wilfully ſhortned in neceſſaries; and when ſhe is <hi>ill reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with blowes. Chriſt</hi> is an abſolute <hi>Lord,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 31. 27</note> as well as an husband, and ſo may correct his Spouſe; but we are onely husbands, and may not do that which can never be done without ſin.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:169476:30"/>
               <p> Now the reaſons why husbands muſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their wives are theſe: Becauſe they are the weaker veſſels. Weakeſt members are moſt ſpared; and brittle veſſels are moſt tenderly uſed. It is true, they are veſſels, therefore they are for uſe: they are helps to pietie, helps to ſocietie, helps to houſe-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and helps to propagation; yet are they weaker veſſels, therefore to be honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as being for the Cloſet, not for the Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</p>
               <p>Beſides they are <hi>heirs</hi> together with their <note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> husbands of the Grace of life. This is the dignitie of that ſexe, that neither male nor female are lookt upon by a different eye in God, but all are one in Chriſt. Yea, would ye not have <hi>prayers interrupted?</hi> then thus honour your wives ſaith <hi>Peter.</hi> Yea, they are <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.</note> the <hi>gifts of God</hi> for all comfort; and ſuch gifts are prized.</p>
               <p>What therefore remains, but that huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands honour their wives. If an husband ſay, my wife is full of weakneſs, therefore honour her as the weaker; a Venice glaſs with good uſage laſteth long.</p>
               <p>If he ſay, ſhe hath bad qualities; love not them, yet honour her, not becauſe ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, but becauſe God commands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:169476:31"/>
               <head>SECT. 13.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond paire in this building of God are Couplings, and they are</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Children,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Parents.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Children next to their duties to God are bound to doe their duties to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. Theſe ſtand,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>In Reverence.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>In Obedience.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>In Thankfulneſs:</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. They owe reverence to their Parents; for acting of which there are,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Duties</hi> which they muſt do.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Sins</hi> which they muſt avoid.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Their Duties are grounded in a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar love, ſuch as <hi>Ruth</hi> had to <hi>Naomi;</hi> and they <note place="margin">Ruth 1.</note> are two, ſtanding in a reverent awe of them, as God ſaith, <hi>Ye ſhall fear every man his mother</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Levit. 19. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>and his father.</hi> God placeth the mother firſt, becauſe they ſooneſt are deſpiſed thorough their own indulgence. Next, they muſt teſtifie this their reverence five wayes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By ſpeaking reverently unto them, as <hi>Iſaac, here am I my father;</hi> and that ſon in the <note place="margin">Gen. 22. Matth. 21. 30. 1 Kings 2. 20.</note> Goſpel, <hi>I goe Sir;</hi> and <hi>Solomon, Aske on my mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:169476:31"/> 2. By humble craving their bleſſings. Though they have no prophetical bleſſings, as <hi>Iſaack</hi> had for <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau;</hi> yet God <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> ſaith, <hi>Honour thy Parents, that thou maiſt live.</hi> God hath promiſed them to be an ordinary means to get life of him for honourers of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By riſing up before them. You know <note place="margin">Prov. 31. 28</note> what <hi>Bathſhebah</hi> ſaith, <hi>Her children riſe up and call her bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. By bowing and baring to them (as ſigns of civil honour.) Thus <hi>Ioſeph</hi> though a mightie Prince, and his father in want, yet <note place="margin">Gen. 48. 12 1 Kings 2. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>bowes to the earth before him,</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> to his mother.</p>
               <p n="5">5. By not witneſſing againſt them, except <note place="margin">Deut. 33. 9.</note> in caſe of Treaſon and Rebellion! for at ſuch a turn, <hi>Levi</hi> ſaw not his father, nor his mother or brethren.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sinnes to be avoyded by children are; Firſt ſetting light by Parents: <hi>Curſed be he,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 27. 16.</note> (ſaith God) <hi>that ſets light of his father,</hi> that is, gives not reſpect to him, as God and nature requires.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Mocking of Parents; <hi>The eye</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 30. 17</note> 
                  <hi>that mocks his father, and deſpiſeth the inſtruction of his mother, let the Ravens pick out, and the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles devour:</hi> and this I ſpeak upon my own knowledge, that I knew a ſonne many yeares who forſook the courſe of his good father, &amp; neglected the counſel of his religious mother, and as he was going homeward from his bowzing companions in the evening, he fell
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169476:32"/> among buſhes, and died before morning, and was found by his friends that ſought him, with his eyes picked out either by <hi>Crows, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> or ſome birds of prey.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Curſing of Parents. <hi>He that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Levit. 20. 9</note> 
                  <hi>his father and mother ſhall die the death,</hi> ſaith God; and our good Saviour doth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Smiting Parents, <hi>For he that ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mark 7. 10 Exod. 21. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>father and mother ſhall die the death.</hi> The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Heathens ſowed ſuch children in a ſack with a Dog, Cat, Viper, and Ape, as Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems of unnaturalneſſe, and drowned them together.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They owe Obedience unto their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: <hi>Obey the father that hath begotten thee, and deſpiſe not thy mother when ſhe is old,</hi> ſaith <note place="margin">Prov. 23. 22. Col. 3. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Solomon: Children obey your Parents in all things,</hi> for this is pleaſing ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi> To O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey is an humble being at the command of Parents, and a patient holding out to the end, as <hi>Iſaack</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi> when he was to be <note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> ſacrificed.</p>
               <p>And this Obedience reacheth to all things to which the commanding power of Parents extends. It muſt be ſhewed in all <hi>good things</hi> for body, ſoul, ſtate, either preſent or future: <note place="margin">Jer. 35. 6. &amp; 18.</note> In things indifferent, as the <hi>Rechabites,</hi> who for it, were looked upon by God with a <hi>good eye:</hi> In harſh and unpleaſing things, as we ſee in <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when he was commanded to go to his envious brethren that loved him not, and <note place="margin">Gen: 37. 13. 14. Gen. 22.</note> in <hi>Iſaack,</hi> who was able enough to reſiſt, yet reſiſted not.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:169476:32"/>
               <p> All the queſtion will be, how far children muſt Obey? And it may be quickly anſwered, <note place="margin">Luke 14. 26. <hi>Puto genus pietatis Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium eſſe pro Domino.</hi> John 2. Deut. 33. 9.</note> ſo far as may ſtand with the <hi>honour of God;</hi> for otherwiſe ye reade of <hi>Hating father and mother;</hi> and ye ſee the beſt pattern Chriſt, who checked his mother, and obeyed not againſt the houre of his father at the beck, and word of his mother.</p>
               <p>Again, they muſt obey ſo far as ſtands with the <hi>honour of Government;</hi> for if a ſon be in place <hi>of honor,</hi> and he commanded baſe things below him, and unſuitable with his ſtate, he may humbly deny: Yea, and ſo far muſt they obey as ſtands <hi>with the honour of the Family.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> God ſaith, <hi>Forſake thy father and thy mother, and cleave to thy wife.</hi> How forſake them? Not forſake the duty <hi>of honouring them,</hi> or the dutie <hi>of helping them;</hi> but the dutie of <hi>Coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation,</hi> when they have a wife of their own; and the duties of adminiſtring their houſhold affairs, when they have Families of their own to provide for.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They owe thankfulneſſe to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, which muſt be held forth in three duties.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in relieving their Parents that they may recompenſe them as <hi>Paul</hi> phraſeth it. Parents helped them when they could not <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 4.</note> help themſelves; ſo muſt they deal by their Parents that are helpleſſe. Thus did <hi>Chriſt, David,</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> Let all children look ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly upon theſe examples to follow them, <note place="margin">John 19. 26 1 Sam. 22. 3 Gen. 47. 12</note> or elſe remember that memorable <hi>ſtory of</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:169476:33"/> 
                  <hi>Luther.</hi> A good Father had put over his ſtate to his ſons in <hi>Germany,</hi> reſerving onely to himſelf a power by turns, to come and take his diet at their Tables. One of his ſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at dinner, and having a <hi>gooſe</hi> before him, ſpied his father coming, and ſet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ooſe</hi> underneath the table till his father was gone again. Then takes he up the <hi>gooſe</hi> which God had wonderfully turned into a <hi>great toad,</hi> which leaped into his face, and notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all his ſtriving, it could not be removed till it had ſtifled him, to make him an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all unthankfull children.</p>
               <p>Secondly, In praying for them. If for all that are in authoritie, why not for them firſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In burying them: therefore it is now grown into a word <hi>Parentare,</hi> to bury Parents; and the ſolemnities are called <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentals.</hi> Thus did <hi>Iacob, Eſau,</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh that all children would be carefull to know theſe things in Gods building, and do them. I know what many children plead for themſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Saith one, my Parents are childiſh and divers.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> So wert thou, and they were glad to pleaſe thee night and day.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> Saith another, my wife will not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Oh, in other things thou canſt rule her, in this thou wilt not, to ſave thy purſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Saith a third, I am not able to do for them. </p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:169476:33"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Indeed above this God requires not; yet know that Parents will beg for children, why not children for Parents?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Saith a fourth, I had no great matter from my Parents.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> For ſhame ſay not ſo, they were a cauſe of thy Being by Generation, of thy Living by Education, and of thy Learning by Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by themſelves or by others. Say no more, but (children) up, and be doing, or elſe remember <hi>Abſalom,</hi> who being unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to his Parents, was hanged betwixt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, as unworthy of either, or both. If this, or the like ſhould be thy caſe, Farewel life, farewel heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 14.</head>
               <p>NExt I come to Parents, and they <hi>muſt not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>provoke their children to wrath, but bring them up in the nurture, and admonition of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, they muſt not provoke them to wrath. Surely this is not by ſuffering them to have their wills: For <hi>a child ſet at liberty</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 29: 15</note> 
                  <hi>makes the mother aſhamed.</hi> Neither is it by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buking them when they do amiſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for not to do this, undoes many a child, as you ſee in <hi>Adoniah.</hi> Neither is it by correcting them, when rebukes will do no good: for he <hi>that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Kings 1. 5, 6. Prov. 13. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſpares the rod, hates his ſon.</hi> Neither it is by keeping them under ſubjection, for this they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169476:34"/> muſt do out of love to God, and their ſouls, or ſinne will grow. What is it then? It is a ſhewing too much rigour and ſeveritie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them.</p>
               <p>As firſt, when they deny to them what by law of Nature belongs to them according to ſtate, as meat, drink, cloth, and breeding. For <hi>if any man provide not for his own, he is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>worſe</hi> (in that) <hi>then an Infidel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, when they burthen them with unjuſt commands. <hi>Saul</hi> command <hi>Jonathan</hi> to <note place="margin">1 Sam. 20. 31. 34.</note> fetch <hi>David</hi> out of a miſchievous heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; and ſo vexed <hi>Ionathan,</hi> that he kept from his meat.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, When they vex them with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful words for what they cannot help; as when <hi>Saul</hi> called his ſonne, <hi>The ſonne of a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 20. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>perverſe rebellious woman.</hi> The fault was <hi>Sauls</hi> own, and not his ſons if he married ſuch a woman.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, when they rage them with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved blowes. <hi>Saul</hi> took up a javelin to throw at <hi>Ionathan,</hi> and (ſaith the Text,) <hi>He</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 20. 33, 34.</note> 
                  <hi>roſe from the table in fierce wrath.</hi> If Parents thus provoke their children to wrath, <hi>they</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>will be diſcouraged</hi> either by dejectedneſſe, or by fearfulneſſe, or by deſperate ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt bring up their children in <hi>Nurture,</hi> and this is a framing of them like <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> men and women. It includeth four things.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:169476:34"/>
                  <item>1. <hi>Learning.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Labour.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Correction.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. They muſt bring their children up in <hi>learning. Paul</hi> was brought up at the feet of <note place="margin">Acts 22. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> and you know the care of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 2. Dan. 1.</note> daughter for <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> for <hi>Daniel:</hi> how much more muſt Chriſtians that know better. The bleſſed Virgin, though ſhe were poore, would not be guiltie; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Luke 4. 16. John 8. 6.</note> we reade of her ſon <hi>Ieſus,</hi> his reading and of his writing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> I know ſome have ſaid, I ſhall leave my children enough, what needs learning? But there is the more need for that.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> The greater the ſhip is, the greater is the fraight; the greater the fraight, the more skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full had the Pilot need to be.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But the poore man will ſay, alas, I cannot bring him up to learning.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Truely the more is the pittie, yet I wiſh them to conſider ſadly two things; whether they do not ſpend two pence, or three pence in a week worſe? and whether learning be not a better portion then wealth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt bring them up in manners. Riches without manners, is but a Pearl in a ſwines ſnout. Therefore here lies Parents next care. If an Heathen when he ſaw a youth carrie himſelf unmannerly, beat his <note place="margin">Cur ſic in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituis?</note> Maſter, ſaying. <hi>Why doe you inſtruct him ſo?</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:169476:35"/> much more are Parents to bee blamed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> If you ask, wherein doe manners ſtand? </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwer, </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>In Silence.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>In Speech.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>In Geſture.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. They muſt learn them to keep ſilence in two caſes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, In giving their betters leave to ſpeak before them. <hi>Elihu</hi> waited till the antients <note place="margin">Job. 32. 4.</note> had done.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in not interrupting others while they are ſpeaking; for he that is <hi>haſtie in his matters,</hi> there is more hope of a fool then of <note place="margin">Prov. 29. 20</note> him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In ſpeech, they muſt learn them to uſe fair ſpeeches, as that yong man to <hi>Chriſt, good maſter,</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> to that high Chriſtian, <hi>moſt noble Theophilus.</hi> To ſpeak modeſtly of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k 10. 8. 17. Luke 1. 3. 1 Sam. 25. 41.</note> as <hi>Abigail</hi> to <hi>Davids</hi> meſſenger, <hi>Let thy handmaid be a ſervant to waſh the feet of the ſervants of my Lord.</hi> To ſalute lovingly, as <hi>Boaz</hi> and his reapers, <hi>The Lord be with you, the Lord bleſſe thee.</hi> And to thank for kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, <note place="margin">Ruth 2. 4.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla, to whom not onely I give thanks,</hi> but all the <note place="margin">Rom. 16. 4.</note> Churches of the Gentiles.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In Geſtures, they muſt learn them, To meet thoſe that come towards them, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did his ſtrangers: To <hi>riſe</hi> before <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 2. Levit. 19. 32. Gen. 18.</note> their elders, To <hi>ſtand</hi> before their betters, as <hi>Abraham</hi> while his gueſts did eat, To <hi>bow</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:169476:35"/> to them to whom they are ſubject, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Kings 2. 19. Luke 14 8.</note> to his mother: and to <hi>give the chief place</hi> to betters, and to offer it to others of cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie. Oh what a bundle of pride would this dig out of childrens hearts before it come to a grown ſurlineſs, and ſcorn.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They muſt bring them up to labour, either of body or of brain. Idleneſſe is a poyſon to all, eſpecially to youth, who by it have leiſure to invent fantaſtical faſhions, or to gaze upon other fools in Iſrael, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them. Water, be it never ſo clean, with ſtanding ſtinks; and while men ſlept, <hi>the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſowed tares.</hi> So long as <hi>Sampſon</hi> warred <note place="margin">Matth. 13.</note> he could never be overcome of the Philiſtims, but when he idled it in <hi>Delilahs</hi> lap, he loſt ſtrength, eyes, and life ere long.</p>
               <p>It is true, to trie a child to too much were ſevere niceneſſe, or paternal crueltie; <hi>for</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13</note> 
                  <hi>when I was a childe, I did as a childe:</hi> But yet they muſt know, as ſtrength of body, and parts increaſeth, they are born to labour, not to loyter.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They muſt ſubject them (as they doe amiſſe) to correction. As it is not enough to plant a Vine, except we prune and dreſſe it: ſo nor is it enough to have children, except we correct them.</p>
               <p>We have the beſt example in the world, and that is <hi>God</hi> correcting his children, who muſt be our pattern. God doth correct them <hi>with the rod of his Sonne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Among the <hi>Romanes</hi> none that were free <note place="margin">Acts 22. 25.</note>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:169476:36"/> born might be whipt, but <hi>God correcteth every</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>ſonne,</hi> and ſo muſt Parents. God correcteth them <hi>in love:</hi> He is angry with nothing in them, but with their ſinnes; and ſo ſhould it be with Parents.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſul Brutus</hi> executed his trayterous ſons <note place="margin">Exuit pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem ut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dueret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulem.</note> with his own hands, he put off the father that he might put on the juſt Judge: but <hi>Eli,</hi> when his ſonnes made themſelves vile, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained them not. <hi>Elies</hi> anger waxed luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm towards his ſonnes, and Gods anger <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. <hi>Ira Ely te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puit in filios ira Dei ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arſit in illum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </note> waxed hot againſt him. He that will not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, will not take a knife (as <hi>Abraham</hi> did,) though God bid him.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>God moderates</hi> his correction. He <note place="margin">Lam. 2,</note> ſtands <hi>like an adverſary,</hi> but in the midſt of anger <hi>he remembers mercy;</hi> and correcteth <note place="margin">Hab. 3.</note> with the <hi>rod of men.</hi> Yea <hi>God</hi> meaſures out corrections anſwerable to ſinnes. He <hi>weighs a path for his anger</hi> by weight, number, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. So ſhould Parents. Though they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect with the rod of men; yet, if ſonnes riſe <note place="margin">Pſal. 78. 50</note> to rebellion, they muſt bring them forth, and caſt the firſt ſtone.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They muſt bring up their children in <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Admonition</hi> of the Lord, to frame them like Chriſtian men, to this end,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>They muſt train them up religiouſly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>They must guard their Religion and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. In training them up religiouſly lies their greateſt care and comfort, by making their Children Gods children.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:169476:36"/>
               <p> If <hi>Damatria</hi> could ſay, <hi>I had rather have a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mallem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere filium mortuum, quam bello inutilem.</note> 
                  <hi>dead ſonne, then to have a ſonne unprofitable for warre:</hi> much more ſhould a Chriſtian ſay, I had rather have none then ſuch as are uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to God.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Aulus Fulvius</hi> ſaid, when his ſonne <note place="margin">Ego te non catilinae ſed patriae genui</note> was in <hi>Catilines</hi> conſpiracie, <hi>I begat thee not for Catiline, but for thy Countrey:</hi> much more ſhould we ſay, I begat not my children for the world, fleſh, and devil, but for God.</p>
               <p>This training them religiouſly doth reſpect two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Their admittance into the Church by Baptiſme. To have a childe the childe of the Church by Baptiſme is the glory of a Chriſtian. He can not with truth, and glory to God think that the children of the Jewes ſhould have a greater priviledge then the children of Chriſtians; therefore as the firſt care of the Jew was for Circumciſion; ſo his firſt care is for Baptiſme and Circumciſion <note place="margin">Col. 2. 11, 12.</note> that is <hi>made without hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Their bringing up in the Church in the fear of God. As in <hi>Ieremiah's</hi> viſions, God firſt ſhewed him the <hi>Rod of an Almond tree,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 1. 11.</note> becauſe it bloſſoms firſt: ſo God likes the dayes of youth to be conſecrated to God.</p>
               <p>Therefore Parents muſt firſt inſtruct them ſo ſoon as they are capable. It <hi>was a Law in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 7. 20. Pſal. 78. 5, 6</note> 
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> that the fathers ſhould teach the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt inſtruct them according to their capacitie. Train up a childe in his <hi>way,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:169476:37"/> ſaith <hi>Solomon;</hi> as <hi>Iacob</hi> drave all his, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 6.</note> to their paces, They are like us in what they are unlike to God. They may die in their youth and folly, and then the ſinnes of their youth will lie down with them in the duſt. They are born blind. The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was the <hi>Father of living ones;</hi> the ſecond <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pater vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventium, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aeterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, patres caecorum.</note> the <hi>Father of Eternitie,</hi> and we are <hi>the Fathers of the blind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our bringing them up in Gods fear, may by Gods bleſſing, be a means of opening their eyes, that they may be turned <hi>from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 28. Col. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>to light,</hi> and brought out of the <hi>kingdome of darkneſſe</hi> into the kingdome of Gods dear Sonne.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They muſt (ſo near as they can) make choiſe of the beſt maſters for them, As <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> had the chief inſtructer for the ſciences of Egypt; ſo <hi>Iehoaſh</hi> had good <hi>Iehojadah.</hi> This (among others) is reckoned a cauſe of <hi>Iulians</hi> Apoſtacie, that he had two wicked Heathens to be his maſters, <hi>Libanus</hi> and <hi>Iamblicus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt guard their Religion, and Pietie three wayes,</p>
               <p>Firſt by putting them <hi>under Gods protection</hi> by dayly prayer.</p>
               <p>Secondly, By providing for them ſome lawfull imployment; for God annointed <hi>Saul</hi> while he was ſeeking his fathers Aſſes; <hi>David</hi> was taken from the ſheepfold; and two famous Prophets, <hi>Eliſhah,</hi> and <hi>Amos</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:169476:37"/> were taken, the one from the plough, the other from the herd.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by diſpoſing of them for the beſt advantage for their ſouls in marriage. We have a precept, <hi>Take wives to your ſonnes, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 29. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>husbands to your daughters;</hi> and the practiſe of <hi>Abraham</hi> for <hi>Iſaac, Manoah</hi> for <hi>Sampſon,</hi> yea, and of <hi>Agar</hi> for <hi>Iſhmael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I now humbly beſeech that all Parents would ply theſe three Rules of <hi>Paul,</hi> and that they would not be <hi>Judaſſes,</hi> under pretence of a kiſſe, to betray their childrens ſouls. But as <hi>Crates</hi> was wont to cry out to the people, <hi>O men whither now away? why take ye ſuch care to gather riches for your children, and have no care to train them up that ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them?</hi> So may we ſay of too many care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Parents among Chriſtians to the ſhame of holy Chriſtianitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:169476:38"/>
               <head>SECT. 15.</head>
               <p>THe laſt paire are as rafters in Gods building, when it comes to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; and are,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Maſters,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Servants.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Servants muſt be obedient to their maſters</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>according to the fleſh.</hi> By Maſters you may not underſtand thoſe that uſurp authoritie over the conſciences of men: for this none muſt doe, and none muſt ſuffer according to <hi>Pauls</hi> rule, <hi>Be not the ſervants of men:</hi> but <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.</note> thoſe that are <hi>Maſters according to the fleſh,</hi> that is, who rule over the body.</p>
               <p>By Servants, you muſt underſtand thoſe that by Covenant cannot diſpoſe of their ſervice as they pleaſe, but muſt be at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of thoſe that hire them. Now, theſe muſt be obedient, of which they muſt weigh,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Ground,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The manner,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The reaſon</hi> of it.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>ground</hi> is that <hi>ſubjection</hi> which is due from the ſervant to the maſter. By this he ſtoops under the authoritie of his maſter, and it muſt be diſcovered three wayes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By inward reverence, his maſter bear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169476:38"/> the Image of Gods ſoveraigntie; in which reſpect God ſaith, <hi>If I be your maſter, where</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 1. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>is my fear?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By <hi>out ward expreſsing of it</hi> in ſpeech and <note place="margin">Luke 17. 7.</note> geſture, as that <hi>wearie ſervant,</hi> when he came from the field, did not refreſh at his pleaſure, but waited upon his maſters leiſure.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By patient bearing of rebukes though bitter, and unjuſt; as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, ſervants be ſubject to your maſters with all fear, <hi>not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 18 19.</note> 
                  <hi>to the good and gentle, but alſo the froward,</hi> for this is thank worthy.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But hath a ſervant no remedy if he be wronged?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>God</hi> forbid, <hi>for the Magiſtrate beareth not the ſword in vain.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If that cannot be had he may withdraw for the preſent, till the ſtorm be over, as <hi>David</hi> from <hi>Saul,</hi> and the Egyptian from the Amalekite, and then come again.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The manner of his obedience is,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Readily.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Pleaſingly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Silently.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Faithfully.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Diligently.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Readily, having their eyes alwayes to their maſters to be directed by a word, or a <note place="margin">Pſ. 123. 2.</note> nod. Thus did the <hi>Centurions,</hi> when he ſaid <note place="margin">Matth. 8. 9.</note> to one goe, he went, to another come, he came; to another, doe this, and he did it:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169476:39"/> when it was otherwiſe with <hi>Jobs</hi> ſervants, <note place="margin">Job 19. 16.</note> according to his complaint, <hi>I called my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and he gave me no anſwer, I entreated him</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Quoad Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentiam Dominorum; quoad Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</note> 
                  <hi>with my mouth</hi> in vain, it was for want of fear, in reference to reverence to their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; and for want of trembling in reference to the judgement of the Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Pleaſingly, pleaſing their maſters in all</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 9. Tit. 2. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>things,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> not as <hi>men-pleaſers</hi> with eye ſervice, but with ſingleneſſe of heart as in <hi>Gods</hi> ſight, as good <hi>Jacob</hi> did to churliſh <hi>Laban.</hi> If you ask wherein they muſt pleaſe them? <hi>God</hi> ſaith, <hi>according to the fleſh</hi> in all lawfull and honeſt things.</p>
               <p>The maſters are over the fleſh, not the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: therefore ſlaves are called bodies, becauſe <note place="margin">Apoc. 18. 13 <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> commands of maſters reach onely to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. The ſervants muſt obey onely in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things. As the dominion of maſters is <note place="margin">Col. 3. 22.</note> limited, ſo is the obedience of ſervants.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Silently, not anſwering again,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 10. <hi>Sit ſervus monoſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Domino.</hi>
                  </note> therefore that rule is good. <hi>Let the ſervant ſpeak in one ſyllable to his maſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet I ſhall ſhew you two things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Wherein ſervants may ſpeak?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Wherein they may not ſpeak?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. They may ſpeak in three caſes; Firſt, when <hi>juſt occaſion</hi> is offered by queſtions: for they are condemned who <hi>when they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand will not anſwer.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 29. 19</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, when they <hi>receive wrong</hi> from
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169476:39"/> their maſters, they may with humble reſpect clear themſelves, as <hi>David</hi> did of treaſon, by <note place="margin">1 Sam. 24. 10, 11.</note> ſhewing his innocencie by three ſignes, the lap of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment, his water pot, and ſpeare.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, when wholſome and good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice may doe their maſters good, as you ſee not onely in <hi>Naamans</hi> ſervants when they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed <note place="margin">2 Kings 5. 13. Job 31. 13.</note> him to follow the Prophets counſel though it ſeemed but mean unto him, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in <hi>Job</hi> when he was in his proſperitie.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They may not ſpeak in two caſes. Firſt, by private mutterings and grumblings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the command of their maſters.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by open croſſing and thwarting them by perverſe and ſnarling words, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke them to anger and diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Faithfully,</hi> as, <hi>Jacob</hi> obeyed <hi>Laban,</hi> by bearing the heat of the day, and burthen of <note place="margin">Gen. 38. 39 40.</note> the night for his good; and <hi>Joſeph</hi> obeyed both <hi>Potiphar,</hi> and the Jaylor, who looked not to any thing under his hand, ſo faithfull was he. This faithfulneſſe ſtands in two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In ſeeking to <hi>encreaſe</hi> their maſters good to their lawful power: for <hi>talents</hi> are <note place="margin">Matth. 25. 27. Tit. 2.</note> put out to the ſervants for the maſters gain.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In not diminiſhing them. They muſt be no pickers and ſtealers, ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> They will ſay, I may make bold with a little which hurts not my maſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> But I ſay, crack conſcience (for a little) which doth a little hurt, and who will truſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169476:40"/> thee in more? If <hi>Achans</hi> toung of gold lye before thee thou wilt not ſpare. <hi>God</hi> delights to ſay to a good ſervant, <hi>Thou haſt been faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>in a little.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But haply thou wilt ſay, my maſter is hard and this provokes me to do otherwiſe then I would.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> I ſay, it matters not, thou goeſt by this way, from the ſervice of an hard maſter, to the ſervice of an harder, The Devil, and what gainſt thou by that?</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Diligently. He that waits on his maſter</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 18. 1 Kings 17. 1. 2 Kings 5. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall be honoured,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi> For this cauſe ſervants are ſaid to ſtand before their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to be alwayes at hand upon every oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: and Heathens painted ſervants <hi>with their hands full of tools</hi> to imply their diligence about any work that their maſters ſet them about.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But you may ask me whether ſervants are never free from this obedience to their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwer, they are not free from the habit of it, ſo long as they are under <hi>Covenant.</hi> Yet they are from the acts of it at three times, when they are the Lords priſoners by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in truth not pretended: when they are to reſt in the night except in extraordinarie caſes; and when they are bound, according to good orders of the Family, to ſerve the Lord either privately with their maſters, or publikely upon the Lords day.</p>
               <p>Now thirdly, the reaſons why ſervants
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169476:40"/> muſt thus obey are theſe. 1. Becauſe thus they honour Chriſt. They are more Chriſts then their maſters; therefore they <hi>obey as the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 6. 1 Pet. 2. 19, 20. Col. 3. 24. 1 Pet. 2. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>ſervants of Chriſt.</hi> 2. Becauſe <hi>this is acceptable to God,</hi> and he will pay better wages then men; for they ſhall <hi>receive the reward of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</hi> 3. Becauſe thereunto they are called, and heartned by Chriſts example, who ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the uttermoſt for our good.</p>
               <p>Oh that all ſervants would learn to be better ſervants then they are or have been, according to theſe directions. I am ſure, if they doe not, at the laſt they will lie down in ſorrow. Oh that they would carefully ſtudie the leſſons of ſervants as they are laid <note place="margin">Col. 3. 1 Pet. 2. Tit. 2, Eph. 6.</note> down in the good word of God! Oh that the patterns of noble ſervants in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture lay before them, as of <hi>Eliezer Abrahams</hi> ſervant, that faithful, praying and diligent man: and of Jacob when he was a ſervant to <hi>Laban,</hi> and of the Centurions ſervants, who were at ſuch a punctual beck. Oh that they would never forget <hi>Pauls</hi> motive, <hi>That you</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 24. Gen. 31. Matth. 8. Tit. 2. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>may adorn the Doctrine of God our Saviour in all things!</hi> Oh that they would think what a diſgrace it is for unworthy ſervants to live under the bleſſed beams of this Goſpel of light, and life. Certainly, if God ſet theſe things home, they would alter their courſe, and be obedient according to Chriſts will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:169476:41"/>
               <head>SECT. 16.</head>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>MAſters muſt give unto their ſervants that which is juſt and equal.</hi> Maſters <note place="margin">Col. 4. 1.</note> muſt make it their firſt care to chuſe ſervants aright. How watchful was <hi>David</hi> for this, when he ſaid, <hi>No deceitful perſon ſhall live in my ſight; he that telleth lies ſhall not abide before</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm 101.</note> 
                  <hi>me?</hi> Truely, ſo ſhould it be with all maſters. This will bleſſe their ſtate as we ſee in <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph;</hi> and the contrarie will poyſon chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and all the comforts of our Families. I heartily pray, that men may be as warie to chuſe them as they are to chuſe ſheep, and ſwine, and dogs, and horſes, according to their races.</p>
               <p>And having choſen them, that they would.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Give them that which is iuſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Give to them that which is equal.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Maſters muſt give to them that which is juſt, that is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what is due to them by poſitive lawes.</p>
               <p>This they muſt perform both,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>In Thought.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>In Words.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>And in Deeds.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. In Thought, not thinking to exerciſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute dominion over them, but ſuch as they
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169476:41"/> muſt account for to God; therefore the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 9.</note> uſeth this motive, <hi>knowing that ye have a maſter in heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In words, both in <hi>commands,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pia, poſsibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onalia.</note> The maſters commands muſt be <hi>pious, poſſible,</hi> and <hi>proportionable.</hi> They muſt be <hi>pious,</hi> that is, things agreeable to Gods will: not as <hi>Sauls</hi> was to <hi>Doeg,</hi> to fall upon <note place="margin">1 Sam. 22. 18. 2 Sam. 13.</note> the Lords Prieſts; nor as <hi>Abſolons</hi> to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to kill <hi>Amnon.</hi> They muſt be <hi>poſsible</hi> of things feazable. Therefore when <hi>Eliezer</hi> ſuſpected the poſſibilitie of his doing after <hi>Abrahams</hi> command, he ſaid, what if the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man will not follow me? <hi>Abraham</hi> replied, <note place="margin">Gen. 24. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>then thou ſhalt be clear.</hi> They muſt be <hi>propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable,</hi> when they command them labour, but not above ſtrength. The poor Iſraelites were ſervants in Egypt, and the Taskmaſter <note place="margin">Exod. 5.</note> cauſed them to gather ſtraw, and make their old tale of brick; this was above ſtrength, and ſo unjuſt. But God ſaith, <hi>over your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Levit. 25. 46.</note> 
                  <hi>you ſhall not rule with rigour</hi> or crueltie. They muſt alſo do juſtice in inſtructions. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants muſt ſerve their maſters as Chriſt, and this they cannot without inſtructions firſt. <hi>Abraham</hi> armed all his trained ſervants, that is, his <hi>Catechized</hi> ſervants, whom he had ſo <note place="margin">Gen. 14. 14</note> well inſtructed, that they would follow him through all dangers; and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> made the ſervants copy out part of <hi>Solomons</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs <note place="margin">Prov. 25. 1.</note> for their rules to follow. If maſters take not this courſe, their ſervants cannot adorn the Doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:169476:42"/> 3. In deeds, as maſters muſt be careful for their ſervants health, if in their ſervice they be ſick, as that good <hi>Centurion</hi> was, who <note place="margin">Matth. 8. 5, 6.</note> went to Chriſt for his help; and in providing <hi>ſufficient meat and drink</hi> for them, as <hi>Solomon</hi> did for his workmen, and the <hi>good houſewife</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Chr. 2. 10 Prov. 31. 15. 1 Cor. 8. 9.</note> for hers according to the equitie of that rule, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe which treadeth out the corn,</hi> and in providing due puniſhment for them according to Law, when they do amiſſe, by which means ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhould be better ſerved: ſo by juſtly <hi>paying them their wages.</hi> This maketh up a <note place="margin">Deut. 15. 13, 14.</note> ſweet harmony betwixt maſters and ſervants, according to that expreſſion of Chriſt, <hi>He agreed with them for a penny,</hi> they make a ſweet <note place="margin">Matth. 29. 2 <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> James 5. 4.</note> ſymphonie or harmonie betwixt them; but the contrary makes a fearful jarre and crie, which God hears.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Maſters muſt give to their ſervants that which is equal, which is due by Charitie, and Chriſtian meekneſſe. For equal doth not comprehend equal honour, and equal offices of love, that is, ſuch as the ſervants performe to the maſter; for this is a good rule; To <note place="margin">Inaequalibus dare aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, inaequale eſt.</note> give equal things to unequal perſons is une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual. But it is to be referred to the mind and manner of doing, that as the ſervant performs his dutie equally, ſo the maſter muſt perform his. The ſervant obeyes as to the Lord, the maſter rules as the Lord piouſly. The ſervant obeyes from the heart willingly; the maſter rules with a mild and fatherly affection.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:169476:42"/>
               <p> Now, this equalitie comprehends foure <note place="margin">Job 31. 15. <hi>Phile. v.</hi> 16. <hi>Habent cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem licet non veſtem.</hi> Job 31. 13. 14.</note> duties. 1. To account that ſervants are of the <hi>ſame mould;</hi> yea, and partakers of the <hi>ſame grace</hi> of Chriſt. They have a common skin, though not a common covering: 2. To hearken to them and <hi>yield to</hi> them when rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and truth is on their ſide. 3. To have reſpect to humane infirmities, as ſickneſſe, age, and paſſions. 4. To give well deſerving ſervants more then is due to them by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and bargain. If they be better then ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, it is but equal that we be better then maſters.</p>
               <p>Oh that all maſters would labour to be ſuch! I ſhall give you but three motives. 1. Our ſervants are <hi>fellow ſervants</hi> with us to God. If the Angel ſaid to <hi>John, I am thy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>fellow ſervant,</hi> much more may the maſter to the ſervant. 2. Death will level us all; yea, it may be will make the ſervant above his maſter, if he be above him in grace: for there <hi>the ſervant is free from his maſter.</hi> 3. Maſters have a Maſter in Heaven, that is <hi>God,</hi> He is <note place="margin">Job 3. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Omniſcient,</hi> and it were impudencie to deal wickedly when he looks on. He is <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Iuſt,</hi> and will not wink at iniquitie, though indulgent maſters will, and doe. He is <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent,</hi> and able to puniſh all iniquitie he hates. The very thought of theſe things ought to make better ſervants, and better maſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:169476:43"/>
               <head>SECT. 17.</head>
               <p>THus I have brought Gods building in a Family from the Rule to the Timber, from the Timber to the Framing, from the Framing to the Foundation, from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to the upper Building, even to the Roof. We are come now to Gods Finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Family, which is by an orderly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment under a good father and mother of a Family.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> You may aske me, why doe you ſay an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly government? For, may not diſorderly perſons be in a good Family? You ask not of (may) as lawfully, approvedly, but (may) as poſſible, and then I anſwer, They may.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> It was holy <hi>Auguſtines</hi> caſe; therefore he writes to the miniſters, ſeniors, and the whole Citie of <hi>Hippo,</hi> that they would not faint in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 137. <hi>quamtumli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet vigile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t diſciplina domus m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ae, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>omo ſum &amp; inter ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. Nec mihi arrogare au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo ut do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus mea melior ſit quam Arca</hi> Noae, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> their courſe, or judge hardly of him for it. <hi>Although</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the diſcipline of my houſe be quiet, and vigilant, yet am I a man, and live amongſt men; neither dare I arrogate to my ſelfe that my houſe ſhould be better then the Ark of</hi> Noah, <hi>the houſe of</hi> Abraham, Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack, Jacob, <hi>and</hi> of Chriſt. Thus may it be alſo with many a good man. Yea, there have been no worſe men in the world, then they that have the beſt means of grace in the beſt Families.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Adams</hi> family there was a murthering <hi>Cain;</hi> in <hi>Abrahams,</hi> a perſecuting <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> In
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169476:43"/> 
                  <hi>Noahs,</hi> a ſcoffing <hi>Cham;</hi> in <hi>Iſaacks,</hi> a profane <hi>Eſau;</hi> in <hi>Davids,</hi> an undutiful <hi>Abſhalom;</hi> in <hi>Mephiboſheths,</hi> a faithleſſe <hi>Zibah;</hi> and in <hi>Eliſhahs,</hi> a lying <hi>Gehazi.</hi> Neither may we wonder at it, becauſe Religion deſcends not by inheritance, for <hi>Adam begat a child in his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 5. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>own likeneſs,</hi> a ſinner like himſelf. Yea, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is the work of God, and he hath other <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 17. 1 Sam. 2. 25.</note> ends, in means of Reformation, then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, as we may ſee in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and in <hi>Elies</hi> ſons.</p>
               <p>Yet what then? Shall not therefore a good father and mother of a Family ſtrive for an orderly government? Yea much more. Ye know what a people God told the Prophets <hi>Jeremy</hi> and <hi>Ezechiel</hi> that they ſhould preach <note place="margin">Jer. 1. 19. Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch. 2. 5. 7. &amp; 3. 7.</note> unto, even as bad as <hi>briars</hi> and <hi>thorns;</hi> yet he did it not to cool their affections, but to make them more zealous: ſo I preſent what poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly may be to whet you to put to all your ſtrength for orderly Families.</p>
               <p>Thus did <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Evah,</hi> whoſe religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Family was called <hi>The face of God.</hi> Thus <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 14. Gen. 18. 19 Joſh. 24. 15. Acts 10. 2.</note> did <hi>Joſhuah, David, Cornelius,</hi> or elſe ſuch high praiſes of them would never have been left recorded for our imitation.</p>
               <p>Conſider therefore ſeriouſly,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>What all Governours of Families muſt doe to this end?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>What either of the Governours muſt doe?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. In general, all Governours of Families
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169476:44"/> muſt be carefull to <hi>looke to themſelves.</hi> If they ſhine not before the reſt, but lie rotting in the dunghil of nature; ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>all have a den of ſwearers, drunkards, lyars, whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, cheaters, and the like, in a Family. For <hi>Jeroboam</hi> will make Iſrael to ſinne, <hi>Auguſtus</hi> will fill his Court with Schollars, <hi>Tyberius</hi> with diſſemblers, and <hi>Julian</hi> with Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates.</p>
               <p>They muſt care again, to be ſuch at home as they ſeem to be in the aſſemblies of Gods people, that is, truely religious. <hi>David</hi> prayes that his people may be corner ſtones, and poliſhed; ſo doe I pray, that all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of Families may be ſuch. They muſt care (as they can) to draw into their Families ſuch as be gracious, or at leaſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to gratious courſes. Though a Family may be named <hi>Good,</hi> from the better part, yet it is beſt when the Canaanites are kept out of it.</p>
               <p>But now ſecondly to come unto particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, ſee what either of the Governours of a <hi>good Family</hi> muſt doe for their parts.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Father of a Family.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Mother of a Family.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:169476:44"/>
               <head>SECT. 18.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe Father of a Family muſt care for three things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That his Family ſerve <hi>God</hi> everie day. When <hi>Joſhuah</hi> ſaith, <hi>(I and my Family will</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 24. 15</note> 
                  <hi>ſerve God)</hi> he doth promiſe, and binde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for every day of his life after. As when <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>thy face will I ſeek,</hi> it binds him for his ever.</p>
               <p>To this end the maſter muſt either teach <hi>(as he can and ought in a private way)</hi> or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 7. 20.</note> that his Family be taught in <hi>Gods will.</hi> The <hi>command of God</hi> requires it: and the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral bond of Chriſtians to exhort, edifie, and comfort one another reacheth unto them. Beſides, the pattern of good men which doth powerfully invite them. See what God ſaith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and it is nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">Gen 18. 19</note> what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith of his father, <hi>Heare (O you children) I give you a good Doctrine:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 4. 1. 2, 3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>for I was my Fathers ſonne, and he taught me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The maſter muſt pray (by himſelf, or other) both with and for his Familie. As the <hi>Patriarch's</hi> were the Princes and Prieſts of the Familie, ſo maſters are chief heads; and truely without Praier they and their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies lie open to the fearful wrath of God; for he <hi>will powre out his wrath upon the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 10. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>that call not upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certainly, maſters are bound to do what good they can for their Families; and how
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169476:45"/> can they ſay ſo to God, when they have not praied for, and with them, which is a ſpecial means.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> All the queſtion wil be <hi>when they muſt do it?</hi> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Not once in a moon, or week, or year; but <hi>pray continually,</hi> argues morning and evening <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.</note> at leaſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They muſt do it in the morning (if they be at home, and well:) becauſe though their family riſe well, yet ere night they may fail, fall ſick, and die Though they ſeem faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful now, they may be faithleſſe, if <hi>God</hi> deliver them not from their own hearts. <hi>Er</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan</hi> were alive in the morning, but dead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore night. <hi>Abimelech</hi> well in the morning <note place="margin">Gen. 38. Jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 9.</note> but his brains almoſt near beat out before night. <hi>Jobs</hi> children well in the morning, <note place="margin">Iob 1.</note> but cruſhed to death before night. How would ſuch accidents ſting maſters Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if they had not cared to prevent ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents by prayer?</p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt doe it in the Evening, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thieves may ſpoil us of our goods, bloud-ſuckers may bereave us of our preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lives, winds may blow down our houſes, fire may devour our goods and perſons, the malicious Prince of the aire may annoy us. Oh how had we need to bring Gods hedge about them by praier, an internal ſleep, or any ſad accident ſhall be the leſſe unwelcome to us and ours.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He muſt care that his Family ſerve God <hi>on the Lords day.</hi> To carrie <hi>Gods</hi> ſenſe diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169476:45"/> I ſhall tender three Rules. 1. <hi>Maſters muſt care that their houſholds keep the Lords day as well as themſelves.</hi> That Law of God, <hi>Thou</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 11. 2</note> 
                  <hi>ſhalt write the Law upon the posts of thy houſe and gates,</hi> doth look two waies.</p>
               <p>To all under government, and telleth them what ſhould be required of them ſo long as they lived in the Family, and to all maſters, what they were to look after from all them that went in and out there. For in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement more ſpecially, what we are bound to do our ſelves, we are alſo bound to be a means to further others in: therefore <hi>God</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thou, thy ſonne, thy daughter, thy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>man-ſervant, thy maid-ſervant, and the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that is within thy gates.</hi> Equitie and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice doth alſo require it: that as they help us in many things, we ſhould help them in the beſt; and as God hath made them ours, ſo we ſhould make them <hi>Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Maſters muſt be careful ſo near as they can, to bring their whole Families to the publick exerciſes of Religion. I mean thoſe that are in a capacitie to make any profit by them.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Jacob</hi> went up to Bethel; he called <note place="margin">Gen 35. 2, 3 Pſal. 42. 4.</note> his people and aſſembled them together; and when <hi>David</hi> went to <hi>the houſe of God,</hi> he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a great train with him; ſo ſhould good maſters doe now. This ſavours of a ſpirit fit for the Goſpel, and theſe times of grace, whereof it is propheſied we ſhould ſay, <hi>Come</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſ. 2. 2, 3. Zach. 8 21 22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>let us goe up to the Houſe of the Lord: Let us</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:169476:46"/> 
                  <hi>goe ſpeedily to pray before the Lord, and ſeek him, I will goe alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Maſters muſt have what care they can over their peoples profiting in Religion: for this is that which gives life to all the reſt. Therefore they ought familiarly to talk with them of what they have heard, as Chriſt did with his Diſciples. They ſhall finde theſe bleſſed benefits by it; <hi>Attention</hi> to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke miniſterie; <hi>Retention</hi> of what is heard; and <hi>Duties</hi> better performed to <hi>God</hi> and to themſelves.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He muſt have care that his Family be kept in a courſe of good order. He muſt have a watchful eye over every ſoul in the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. If <hi>Solomon</hi> would have them <hi>to take heed to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 23</note> 
                  <hi>their herds, and to know the ſtate of their flock<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s;</hi> much more of their people. Surely God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this in <hi>Job,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>It may be my</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iob 1.</note> 
                  <hi>ſonnes have ſinned, and blaſphemed God in their hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He muſt alſo ſee the orders of Gods word to be obſerved in it. And if there be a ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> he muſt out of doores with him: <note place="margin">Pſalm 101.</note> or if ſuch as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of, he muſt not let them abide in his ſight, ſo farre as he hath power to help.</p>
               <p>If a King were to come to thy houſe, and there were ſome traitour in it, wouldſt thou not diſcard him? how much more muſt thou have care to caſt off preſumptuous ſinnefull traitours, ſeing God muſt come and dwell with thee, or elſe thou dieſt for it?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:169476:46"/>
               <head>SECT. 19.</head>
               <p>AS for the Miſtreſſe, or good wife, God muſt have her keep an orderly Family alſo.</p>
               <p>To this end,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>She muſt ordinarily keep at home.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>She muſt govern the houſe in her place.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. She muſt ordinarily keep at home. The <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 5.</note> harlot <hi>ſits at the doore,</hi> and <hi>walks idling</hi> in the ſtreets: but <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid of his wife, <hi>ſhe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 7. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>in the Tent.</hi> And indeed a wife is fitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <hi>to a ſnaile;</hi> not becauſe ſhe muſt be <note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> ſlow, and ſluggiſh as a ſnaile, nor becauſe ſhe muſt be fowle and ſluttiſh, where ſhe goes, as a ſnaile; not becauſe ſhe muſt dwell alone from her husband, as a ſnaile, but be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auſe <hi>ſhe carries her houſe upon her backe,</hi> to ſhew where her mind and ordinarie abode muſt be.</p>
               <p>For gadding brings to harlotrie, as we ſee in <hi>Dinah,</hi> who by gadding came crackt home; and gadding makes idle and buſie bodies, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Going about idlely from houſe to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 13</note> 
                  <hi>houſe, and being buſie bodies.</hi> What? Idle and buſie too? How can that be? Idle in their own affairs, and buſie in other folks matters.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But you may ask, muſt they immure and impriſon themſelves up in their houſes?</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:169476:47"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> No ſurely, they may goe abroad in foure caſes. To holy meetings for the duties of Godlineſſe; thus did the good <hi>Shunamite,</hi> and <hi>Hannah.</hi> To friendly meetings for vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting one another; ſo the bleſſed Virgine viſited <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and other neighbours viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Luke 1. 39. 40, 48.</note> her. For houſhold neceſſaries in her charge; ſo the <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> woman came to Chriſt for her daughter, and the wife of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> came to the Prophet for her childe. And with her husband, when he ſhall require her, as <hi>Sarah, Rebeckah, Naomi,</hi> and the bleſſed Virgine did. Yet muſt they not be from home idly, or frequently.</p>
               <p n="2">2. She muſt govern the houſe in her place, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy are they to have good</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 14</note> 
                  <hi>wives, and worthy to be puniſhed with worſe, who deprive them of all Houſhold government, and uſe them onely as ſervants and drudges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> If I be asked, how I would have her go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern? </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwer from the Scriptures, <hi>By exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> her ſelf in ſome profitable imployment, <hi>as ſeeking wooll and flaxe, and labouring cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 31. 13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>with her hands, being like a Merchants ſhip that fetcheth her food from a farre:</hi> By <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing her maids work</hi> and overſeeing them in it. For if <hi>Heſter</hi> appointed her maides re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <note place="margin">Heſt. 4. 16. Prov. 31.</note> work, ſurely ſhe would not fail in the reſt; and by <hi>ordering her children</hi> and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in wiſedome, as that good Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife <note place="margin">Prov. 31. 26 27.</note> did.</p>
               <p>Oh how gloriouſly is <hi>Gods</hi> building fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169476:47"/> when it is thus ordered? It is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to provide for the bodies of them under you, but ſpecially for their ſoules: therefore be vigilant to pull downe the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues of Satan in your Families; let the Devil be caſt out. Bring in the private exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of Religion into them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cornelius,</hi> brought in prayers and almes; <note place="margin">Acts 10. 2.</note> there is one.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Bereans,</hi> ſearched the Scriptures when <note place="margin">Acts 17. 11</note> they had heard; there is another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eunice,</hi> Catechized her childe, there is a <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 15.</note> third.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſung a Pſalme in his Family after <note place="margin">Matth. 26. 29.</note> ſupper; there is a fourth.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, labour ſincerely to keep the way <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>of God</hi> publikely and privately in your fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and then that honourable Inſcription will come to you, which came to <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcilla, To the Church that is in thy houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>Thus is Gods building finiſhed.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:169476:48"/>
               <head>SECT. 20.</head>
               <p n="4">4. LEt this building be but furniſhed with <hi>Gods furniture,</hi> and then ye have <hi>The Lords building of the houſe,</hi> and they ſhall not labour in vain that build it.</p>
               <p>Now this houſe is furniſhed two waies.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>By getting goods.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>By giving goods.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>This may ſeem to be a Paradoxe; but I ſhall ſmooth it before I leave it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We may get <hi>good</hi> ſixe wayes.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>By lending.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>By borrowing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>By ſelling.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>By buying.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>By letting.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>By hiring.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>And if ye doe them according to <hi>Gods Rule,</hi> ye furniſh <hi>the Houſe of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. As for lending, <hi>We must lend, looking for</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luke 6. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>nothing again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But put caſe we doe, can lending, be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of an houſe, when in lending we part with our own?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Yes, very well; for the righteous is liberal, and lendeth, and <hi>his ſeed doth inherit the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm 37.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:169476:48"/>
               <p> To conceive the Rule then, weigh;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>What is meant by lending?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>What is meant by looking for nothing?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Why we muſt ſo lend?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Lending ſtands either in turning over <hi>of the propertie of goods to another to ſpend,</hi> upon condition of returning the ſame in kind, or worth, after the time ſet, as money, victuals; or in turning over the uſe of a thing to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for a time, to be returned the ſame in number and worth at the time appointed, as when we lend any utenſil; For lending com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Mutuum,</hi> that is, <hi>Meum,</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi> or <hi>ex meo tuum;</hi> now mine, now thine, to return in kinde or worth: Next <hi>Commodatum,</hi> mine in poſſeſſion, and thine in uſe for a time free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be reſtored in the ſame.</p>
               <p>This lending is a free putting over: for this is the nature of lending, as Chriſt ſaith here; and thus it is diſtinguiſhed from buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſelling, letting, hiring, changing, and all mercenarie acts; and it is for a time, to diſtinguiſh it from free giving which is for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and it is but till the time appointed, and this is juſt. Then it is no longer ours, but to be reſtored.</p>
               <p n="2">2. About <hi>looking for nothing</hi> again, I ſhall clear three points.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:169476:49"/>
                  <item>1. <hi>What we may look for again?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>What we may not look for again?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>How it appears to be Chriſts ſenſe?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. We may look for again. Firſt what <note place="margin">1. <hi>Mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ui ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitatem.</hi> 2 Kings 4.</note> juſtly anſwereth to the thing lent: therefore <hi>Eliſha</hi> chargeth the widdow to pay her debts.</p>
               <p>Secondly <hi>An action of debt,</hi> if they can pay <note place="margin">2. <hi>Ream a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem.</hi>
                  </note> it and doe not; and if there be no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; for this is one of the ends of judicature, by which Law is adminiſtred, and which is good if it be uſed lawfully, becauſe the ſword <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> is to defend the oppreſſed.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>The like courteſie</hi> in times of <note place="margin">Amorem &amp; gratitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> need; this is but equal; <hi>ſupport one another in Love;</hi> doe good one to another.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Love</hi> and thankfulneſſe. This <hi>Paul</hi> payed cheerfully unto <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilla,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 16. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>unto whom I give thanks.</hi> Theſe things we may look for; yet here we muſt be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that our hearts do not carry us to lend for theſe things ſake, for then are we ſelfe-ſeekers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We may not look for again, The like good turn to be done to us for lending ſake, as lending; becauſe it is a free act: nor any gain for lending, as if we wiſht that what we lent would come laughing home: becauſe this overthrows the nature of lending, which ought to be free; and this takes away the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of lending, which is onely that the <note place="margin">Exod. 22. 14, 15.</note> lender be no loſer.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:169476:49"/> 3. It appears that this is <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſenſe, in the word <hi>Nothing;</hi> becauſe by this rule he doth onely oppoſe the <hi>Phariſes,</hi> who were <note place="margin">Luke 6. 32, 33, 35.</note> willing to lend onely to them that were able and willing to benefit them again, and from whom they looked for the like.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The reaſons why we muſt ſo lend, are taken from Chriſt himſelf, which are; Firſt, the command of God. Secondly, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>of Chriſt, your reward ſhall be great in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luke 6. 34, 35.</note> 
                  <hi>Heaven.</hi> Thirdly, the ſign of ſonne-ſhip; ye ſhall <hi>be the children of the Higheſt.</hi> Fourthly, the example of God, he is <hi>kind to unthankful ones.</hi> Fifthly, and a difference from ungodly men, <hi>ſinners lend to ſinners to receive as much again;</hi> but you are not in communion with ſuch, therefore you muſt look for <hi>Nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now from this rule of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> there is a double inference,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That lending is a dutie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That lending muſt be free.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. It is a dutie, becauſe Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Lend;</hi> and we muſt take his word. To help you therefore in it, I ſhall ſhew you,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Who must lend?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>To whom we muſt lend?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Why we muſt lend?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Every one muſt not lend; but firſt, he <hi>that hath this worlds goods of his own.</hi> This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes ſervants, they muſt not lend their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169476:50"/> 
                  <hi>goods:</hi> children, they muſt not lend their Parents <hi>goods:</hi> Condemned perſons, they muſt not lend confiſcated goods though they were their own; unlawfull getters may not lend unlawfully gotten goods, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſhould reſtore them to the true owners. Secondly, He that hath wiſedome to lend for the good of the publick body, he muſt lend when he hath to lend of his own.</p>
               <p>This excludes all unthriftie perſons; who are under tutours and governours, and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who want wiſedom to mannage ſuch a work.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe that may lend, muſt not lend to thoſe to whom they can doe no good; as to Spend-thrifts who live in wicked courſes; to Gallants, who ſpend all upon back and bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; to men not able to mannage their trades; for ſo they pull down a Common-wealth; to men not able to pay again; theſe are not the objects of lending, but of giving; to men that live above their ſtates; for this feeds pride, and ruineth them; and to men that ſeek lending for ſpending, as Drunkards, who ſpend on the Lords Day in drinke and Tobacco, more then they get in the week to pay debts.</p>
               <p>But if ye lend, ye muſt lend to thoſe to whom ye may doe good, whether they be <hi>good rich,</hi> to whom you may lend out of cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie; <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>or good poore,</hi> to whom (if ye are able) ye muſt lend out of mercy, for <hi>a good man</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 112. 5</note> 
                  <hi>ſhewes favour and lendeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:169476:50"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect: </seg>
                  </label> If ye ſay, <hi>I can not lend to all.</hi> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> That is true, therefore <hi>a good man lendeth, and will guide his affairs with judgement.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 112. 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The reaſons why they that may, and can muſt lend, are becauſe it is a commanded dutie, <hi>If thy brother be poore, thou ſhalt not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 15. 7. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>harden thy heart, but thou ſhalt lend unto him ſufficient:</hi> Yea, becauſe by this means we provide for our children, <hi>The righteous is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>merciful, and lendeth, and his ſeed inherits the bleſsing:</hi> and becauſe we may not be a means <hi>to multiply the poore,</hi> and ſo, leſſen the givers. A little lent, many times, by Gods bleſſing and mans induſtrie, may make a giver, and keep from povertie.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is alſo inferred neceſſarily that <hi>lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing muſt be free:</hi> looke for nothing, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore receive but thine own. Look for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, therefore lend for nothing. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay, but that they who have plentie of money may, not by lending, but by another contract, place out their money with thoſe that have plentie of trade, by which they make gain, and receive profit by it: for there is neither reaſon nor conſcience, but that when money is made fruitful the owner ſhould have a ſhare in the fruit: yet doe not as <hi>common <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers,</hi> who ſtrive to take this excellent dutie of lending out of the world. For it takes from it three things; The <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of lending which is free. The <hi>Equitie</hi> of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nullo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſito praetio</hi> Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d. 22. 14. 15.</note> lending, which is onely to make the lender no loſer, whereas they are gainers: and <hi>The</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:169476:51"/> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of lending; for if they can lend for gain, no man will lend freely.</p>
               <p>Deal you better with lending, and uſe this dutie well which Chriſt requireth. In gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, doe it out of true love, not ſelf love: for others good, whether you lend to rich or poore. In particular, lending is double: <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> and bare, upon a word of entreatie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and no more <hi>Cloathed</hi> and palliated with pawnes, pledges, bonds or bils. It is not abſolutely lawful in all caſes to take pawnes and pledges; therefore mark the Scripture expreſſions, <hi>If at all</hi> thou take a <note place="margin">Exod. 22. 26. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut. 24. 6. ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 17. Iob 24. 13. Prov. 20. 16</note> rayment for a pledge, <hi>you muſt not take the upper garment, or nether milſtone, nor a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes rayment,</hi> nor a widdowes Oxe: That in <hi>Solomon, take his garment that is ſuretie for a ſtranger, and take a pledge of him for a ſtrange woman,</hi> is not ſpoken of a poore borrower, but of a deſperate <hi>foole</hi> that will raſhly be bound for a ſtranger, and wickedly get mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for harlotrie. But if thou do take pawns, things of neceſſary uſe are not to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held though they pay thee not. For <hi>rayment</hi> pawned muſt be delivered; and the <hi>milſtones,</hi> and ſo any neceſſary inſtruments by which a <note place="margin">Exod. 22. 26.</note> living is gotten; becauſe the <hi>life</hi> is gotten and maintained by them. Uſe lending ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording <note place="margin">Deut. 24. 6. 12, 13.</note> to theſe Rules and proſper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:169476:51"/>
               <head>SECT. 21.</head>
               <p n="2">2. AS for <hi>Borrowing,</hi> you muſt if you would furniſh with <hi>God,</hi> pay juſtly when due, and fully without defalcation. For this is your rule, <hi>O we nothing to any man, but</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>that ye love one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> You may ſay, then I may not <hi>borrow</hi> at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Yes ſurely, elſe why ſhould God command lending: thus therefore you muſt underſtand it; owe nothing that is due to be paid with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leave. Some will pay, but not all. Some pay at laſt, but not juſtly; ſome pay nothing but ill words.</p>
               <p>But to remedy all, Firſt labour to owe as little as poſſibly you can; for it is a baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to borrow, <hi>The borrower is a ſervant to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>the lender,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, If you owe any thing, labour to pay: ſo long as thou art in debt, <hi>thou art</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 6. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>in a ſnare, deliver thy ſelf</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon:</hi> abate thy expenſes in meat, drink, clothing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment till thou be at libertie.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, think often how unjuſt it is that thou ſhouldſt be better in thy eſtate by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans loſſe.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, let that note of a godleſſe man ſtare upon thy Conſcience to affright thee, <hi>The wicked borrowes, and payes not again.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 37. 21.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Uſe what is lent thee ſo, as thou reſtore it well, and honeſtly. To this end, uſe it to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169476:52"/> that end it was lent thee, and reſtore it ſafely at the time appointed. This is juſt according to Gods Word, and thy Conſcience, and will bring Gods bleſſing to the building of the Family by it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 22.</head>
               <p n="3">3. FOr buying, ſelling, letting, hiring, <hi>God</hi> gives one general rule; <hi>Defraud not, or goe not beyond your brother in any matter.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſ. 4. 6</note> Dealing is ſo intertwiſted with deceit, as if tradeſmen generally had another rule to walk by, from another Bible of their own deviſing.</p>
               <p>But God will have an account from every tradeſman of this rule which he hath given them.</p>
               <p>Enquire,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Who is meant by our Brother?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>What is meant by going beyond,</hi> or <hi>defrauding?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Why you muſt not doe it?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. By brother, you muſt underſtand every one that you are to deal with. <hi>Have we not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 10. <hi>Caveat em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptor.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>all one Father?</hi> and ſo we are all brethren. That ſpeech therefore is rotten, <hi>Let the buyer beware.</hi> he was a ſtranger, he ſhould have looked better to it. I have read of ſome Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens who would teach their children to lie
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169476:52"/> to ſtrangers and enemies, but not to friends, But theſe children forgot this diſtinction, and made bold to lie to their beſt friends. ſo we finde it in tradeſmen, who miſtaking <hi>brother</hi> for a friend onely, deceive poore ſtrangers, and out of cuſtome make bold with their friends, and give them a curriſh and unkind nip upon this account, <hi>that he is my friend that I can gain by.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By <hi>going beyond,</hi> or defrauding, you muſt underſtand over-reaching, cozening in bargaining one with another, as in buying, ſelling, letting, and hiring.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The reaſons why ye may not doe it may be theſe:</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe <hi>God is the avenger of all ſuch,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4. 6 <hi>Qui tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum timet eſt inimicus Iuſtitiae.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Paul</hi> hath it. I know <hi>He that doth a dutie onely for feare, is an enemy of juſtice:</hi> Yet an eye to the puniſhment is one ingredient which muſt have a ſtroak here. And this is moſt true, where mans juſtice fails, Gods venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance comes in to make a ſupply as in the caſe of <hi>Ahab, Ieſabel,</hi> and <hi>Naboth.</hi> Gods rules are excellent; <hi>Rob not the poore becauſe he is poore,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>for the Lord will plead their cauſe, and ſpoile the ſoul of them that ſpoyled them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe there is a kind of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie or worſe filth in it. The Law ſaith, that <hi>Nature hath made a marriage betwixt the heart</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rba con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiuntur in adulterio.</note> 
                  <hi>and the tongue;</hi> therefore <hi>when the heart and tongue doe diſagree, words are conceived in adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie:</hi> ſo may we ſay betwixt words and truth of things in bargaining, ſo farre as acts are
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169476:53"/> produced without the concurrence of words and truth, they are brought forth in adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie.</p>
               <p>If therefore there muſt be no defrauding in any matter, you muſt firſt <hi>be equal in ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this end weigh,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Who muſt ſell?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>What muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ſold?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>How it muſt be ſold?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. For the perſon that muſt ſell, he muſt be a juſt profeſſor, one that ownes a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie by good r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght, and hath judgement to doe it. This is but equal, and ſo excludes thieves, fools, and all that have gotten goods unjuſtly, which muſt be reſtored (if they would have pardon) and not ſold.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That muſt be ſold which may be valued with money. Not the graces and gifts of God either <hi>miraculous</hi> or <hi>ordinarie,</hi> as the <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings 5. 20. Acts 8.</note> 
                  <hi>of ſinne,</hi> or the like, of which ſale <hi>Teceliris</hi> was a great Merchant for the Pope in the daies of <hi>Luther,</hi> no nor juſtice muſt be ſold by bribery, which is to be reckoned for in too many places of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udicatures, nor muſt lies be ſold by falſe witneſſes, or ungodly Lawyers; nor courteſie, mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> time, by the common Uſurers; but that which may be valued by money.</p>
               <p>Yea, Thirdly, It muſt be worth the mony we ſell it for.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> If you ask how it ſhall be valued? </p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:169476:53"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwer, the worth of a thing is double; Natural, and ſo a living Flie by natural worth is of more value then all dead gold; uſual, and this is valued by the <hi>goodneſſe</hi> of the thing, if it be not counterfeit and vitious, as <note place="margin">Eſd. 1. 22. Amos 8. 6.</note> when wine is mixed with water, droſſe with ſilver, chaff, and refuſe with wheat: and by the rareneſſe of a commoditie; in this caſe <note place="margin">2 Kings 5. 18. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>a cab of Doves dung,</hi> and an <hi>Aſſes</hi> head is valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above their natural or uſual worth. Yet no commoditie muſt be made rare by <hi>our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſsing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 11. 26</note> 
                  <hi>and foreſtalling; for he that withdrawes the corn hoping for a dearer market, the poore ſhal curſe him, but bleſsing ſhall be to him that ſells it;</hi> and ſo for other commodities.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But you will ſay, <hi>May a man in no caſe ſell for more then a commoditie is worth?</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I know but one caſe in which they may, and that is when by the ſale of it a man is damnified; for then the loſſe may be repaired; otherwiſe the very <hi>Thuriaci</hi> made the ſeller ſweare before the Magiſtrate, that he ſold for no more then his commodity was worth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But ſtill you ſay, may not a man ſell for more then it is worth, <hi>when he ſels for time?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> This ſelling for time undoes many a man, in making him a debter before he knowes how to pay, and embezels the ſtate of many an heire, who flouriſheth for a time, and ſels his inheritance by leiſure. But you muſt know that there is a fourefold price of commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. <hi>Pious,</hi> betwixt brother and brother; <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dium, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentatum.</note> betwixt man and man, <hi>Rigid,</hi> betwixt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169476:54"/> Chriſtian and Turk; and <hi>Augmented</hi> above theſe three. The firſt three exceed not Juſtice, if a tradeſman be worſted by delay. But the fourth doth. For it biteth and devoureth for times ſake, and which is not in a mans power to ſell.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As the <hi>how</hi> and manner of ſelling, it <hi>muſt not be deceitfully</hi> in word or deed. <hi>Not in word,</hi> by flattering the buyer, or praiſing the commoditie above its worth, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing the faults. Not <hi>in Deeds,</hi> when they <note place="margin">Eſ. 1. Amos 8.</note> deceive in the kind, as by ſelling <hi>dros for ſilver or refuſe for wheat;</hi> or in the <hi>Qualitie,</hi> as by making it ſeem better then it is by falſe gloſſes, falſe lights, or by comparing it with <note place="margin">Prov. 11. 1. Amos 8. 4, 5, 6, 7. Levit. 19. 35, 36. Deut. 25. 14, 15.</note> worſe: or in the <hi>Quantitie,</hi> by falſe <hi>weights</hi> and <hi>meaſures,</hi> both which are alike abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But then you will ſay, we ſhall never be rich. </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> You know not that, remember a good Proverb, <hi>that light gain makes an heavie purſe:</hi> And forget not two excellent Proverbs of <hi>Solomon, An heritage haſtily gotten ſhall not be</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 20. 21 Prov. 28. 20</note> 
                  <hi>bleſſed,</hi> and <hi>a faithful man ſhal abound with bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings: but he that makes haſt to be rich, ſhall not be innocent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:169476:54"/>
               <head>SECT. 23.</head>
               <p n="2">2. IF there muſt be no defrauding in any matter, you muſt <hi>equal in buying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this end conſider.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The perſon of whom you must buy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The thing you buy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The manner of buying.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. You muſt onely buy of him that hath right to ſell, whatſoever pennie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth you may have, you muſt not (as near as poſſibly you can) <hi>buy ſtolne and uniuſtly got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten goods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you doe, you doe communicate with him in ſinne, and countenance him in it. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what <hi>God</hi> blames, <hi>Thou ſaweſt a thief,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 50. 18. Prov. 29. 24</note> 
                  <hi>and runneſt with him;</hi> and what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that is partner with a thief, hates his owne ſoul:</hi> Yea, if you doe, you bind your ſelves to loſſe, <hi>by Reſtitution,</hi> though you have paied for it. For ye muſt reſtore that which is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans, how precious ſo ever it be to you, and ſeek your remedie of the ſeller. If you ſay you have bought it. You may alſo buy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mans houſe and lands, ſhal you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore poſſeſſe them. So nor ought you to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe any things that is another mans right, howſoever it be made yours. If all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt perſons and plunderers in theſe times, who without martial warrant have gotten
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169476:55"/> eſtates by this way would think ſadly of it, their creſts would ſoon fall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider the thing bought. It muſt be <hi>a thing to be ſold,</hi> not the gifts of God, nor remiſſion of ſinnes, nor holy orders; but a <note place="margin">Acts 8. 18, 19.</note> thing to be ſold; and a <hi>thing worth no more then we buy it for,</hi> at leaſt between brother and brother. <hi>Amos</hi> blames them that buy <hi>the poore</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Amos 2. &amp; 8. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>for ſilver, and the needi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for ſhooes.</hi> This is done when ye ſet ſmall prices upon poore peoples works, and commodities, which is a crying ſinne of theſe times; and when great prizes are ſet upon ſuch commodities as the poore muſt buy and live upon, which is as crying a ſinne as the former. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ob</hi> ſaith, If I have eat the fruits of the land <hi>without ſilver</hi> (except it were given him) let thiſtles grow <note place="margin">Job 31. 39. 40.</note> in ſtead of wheat, and cockles in ſtead of barley. Moſt people care not how deare they ſell, and for how little they buy. They would have it for leſſe then it coſt the ſeller, they cannot endure honeſt gains. But they will finde this to be unequal, and that it will breed gravel in their teeth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The manner of buying muſt be laſtly conſidered, and muſt be void of all deceit, either in word or deed. It muſt not have deceit in words: for the buyer muſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe and diſpraiſe the ware below the worth. If he doe, <hi>Solomon</hi> puls him by the ſleeve; <hi>It is naught, it is naught ſaith the buyer, but when</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 20. 14</note> 
                  <hi>he is gone he brags of his penny worth.</hi> It muſt not have deceit indeed by paying counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169476:55"/> and clipt coine, or leſſe then they agree for; both are faults of the miſerable wretches of this time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 24.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> IF there muſt be no defrauding in any matter; you muſt be <hi>Equal in letting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this end Conſider,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>What letting is?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>How it muſt be performed?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Letting is the putting over the uſe of a thing to another for a price, the propertie remaining in our ſelves.</hi> I ſay, for a price to diſtinguiſh it from lending which is free I ſay, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie remaining, to diſtinguiſh it from lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of money, wherein the property in laying of it out, paſſeth away.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This letting muſt be performed upon theſe termes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that which is let muſt <hi>be fit for the uſe for which it is let.</hi> To let a fool or idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to doe a wiſe mans buſineſſe is unjuſt. To let a lame, dul, weake horſe, to doe a ſound quick horſes work is unjuſt. To let barren and ill conditioned Land, for good and fruitful; or to let an houſe that is readie to fall, for a ſufficient one, are unjuſt: we doe not as we would be done unto.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that muſt be lett <hi>whoſe</hi> uſe muſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169476:56"/> be diſtinguiſhed from the propertie, that the <hi>Letter</hi> may have his own again, which can not be in money.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In letting profit muſt be ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned, that he that hires may be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently recompenſed for his labour, and charge. <hi>Solomon</hi> let his Vineyard in Baalhamon to keepers, ſo, as he had <hi>A thouſand pieces of ſilver</hi> for his Rent, and the keepers <note place="margin">Cant. 8. 11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Two hundered,</hi> for their labour, and charge. But if we look to moſt Landlords now, we ſhall finde ſuch pennie worths, that the tenant labouring never ſo hard, can ſcarcely live.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, He that is the Letter muſt bear the hazard of the thing let, if it miſcarrie not thorough the hirers fault: therefore they are unjuſt who exact recompenſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <note place="margin">Exod. 22. 15.</note> Covenant. Certainly, <hi>Laban</hi> was wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who would not ſtand to a plain bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with <hi>Jacob</hi> about the diſcoloured ſheep, <note place="margin">Exod. 30. 20. to v. 3. c. 31.</note> though by his care <hi>Laban</hi> had been made rich. Such Landlords, and Letters may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, but not be built by God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:169476:56"/>
               <head>SECT. 25.</head>
               <p n="4">4. IF there muſt be no defrauding in any matter, you muſt be <hi>Equall in hiring:</hi> and becauſe hiring is of two ſorts, I ſhall ſhew that you muſt be equal in both.</p>
               <p>Firſt, If you hire <hi>perſons for labour,</hi> you muſt allow an equal ſtipend. Their labour is great as <hi>Jacobs,</hi> and the labourer is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie <note place="margin">Gen. 31. 6. 39. 40. Levit. 19. 13. Deut. 42. 14, 15. James 5. 4.</note> of his hire. You muſt <hi>(if he be poore)</hi> give it him without delay. <hi>The workemans hire,</hi> (If his work be done) <hi>Thou ſhalt not withhold till morning,</hi> ſaith God. If you doe, God calls it <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> and that ſin <hi>Cries</hi> as well as others.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in hiring of things: Firſt, you muſt <hi>acknowledge God</hi> the great Landlord, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>The earth is the Lords, and the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 24. 1</note> 
                  <hi>fulneſſe thereof.</hi> This will breed Conſcience in the uſe of it, as if ye had hired it of him immediately. Secondly, you muſt uſe the thing hired in that manner, and to that end for which it was let, both in regard of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie and owner.</p>
               <p>It was a great indignitie when the <hi>Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder</hi> ſent his ſervants to receive <hi>Fruites</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording <note place="margin">Matth. 21. 33, 34, 35.</note> to the bargain, and they were ill entreated and perſecuted. Theſe reſpected not the ends of their hiring, and were uſed accordingly; ſo may juſtly all unjuſt hirers be ſerved in the end.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:169476:57"/>
               <p> Secondly, You muſt <hi>reſtore</hi> and deliver it up at the time appointed. The Parable of the <hi>Talents</hi> teacheth thus much where you <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tth. 25.</note> ſee the <hi>Talents</hi> were called for, and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Owner, with the improvement of them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, You muſt make what was hired good, if it have miſcarried thorough your default. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od requires of <hi>things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted</hi> unto your truſt; much more of things <note place="margin">Exod. 22. 12.</note> which are hired by you.</p>
               <p>Oh, that all this Juſtice were in fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l uſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But it muſt be confeſſed that it is too great a ſtranger till death comes, and the Books are opened, and then, many times it is too late, when men are in as bad a caſe as they who call to the mountains to fall upon them, and the hills to cover them?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:169476:57"/>
               <head>SECT. 26.</head>
               <p>THus you have had the furniſhing of Gods building by getting; now ſecondly, you ſhall have it by giving goods.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> You will ask, Whether a man can furniſh an houſe by parting with what he hath?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwer yes; let God be true, and every man a lier.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Caſt thy bread upon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.</note> that is, the poore, in reſpect of multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and moyſture by crying for bread; <hi>and after many dayes thou ſhalt finde it. Paul</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>What a man ſoweth he ſhall reape;</hi> and <hi>he that ſoweth bountifully, ſhall reap bountifully;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 6.</note> and <hi>Solomon</hi> again, <hi>what a man gives to the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 19. 17</note> 
                  <hi>poore God will pay him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, for giving, remember that ſpeech; <hi>It is a bleſſed thing to give, rather then</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 20. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>to recieve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From hence I ſhall render two Rules a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout giving.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>There is a giver, as well as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>To be a giver is bleſſed, rather then to be a receiver,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. There is a giver certainly; <hi>For the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 2. Matth. 5. 42</note> 
                  <hi>rich and poore meet together, and God is the maker of them both.</hi> He hath charged the one ſort to give; he taketh order for the <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 7. Eſ. 58. 7. Luke 12. 13.</note> other ſort by moving for relief; <hi>Break thy bread to the hungrie;</hi> call <hi>the poore;</hi> and by ordering relievers to the beſt advantage <hi>of</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:169476:58"/> 
                  <hi>the poore,</hi> He gives alſo Patterns of both, and <note place="margin">Acts 6. 1. 2, 3.</note> that amongſt his own people. He tells you of <hi>Abraham</hi> the purchaſer, <hi>Jacob</hi> that had enough, <hi>Solomon</hi> that had gold like ſtones; others who have either been alwaies poore, as <hi>Paul</hi> who ſaith, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto this houre we hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger;</hi> and <hi>Lazarus;</hi> or been <hi>made poore,</hi> as they <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4 11 Heb. 10. 34 &amp; 11. 37.</note> that <hi>ſuffered the ſpoiling of their goods,</hi> and wandred in ſheep skinnes, and goat skinnes. All which God doth order for the exerciſe of the grace of liberalitie, and mercy in ſome; and of faith, patience, and contentment in others. Therefore be you thankfull in both; be you content: and holy in either becauſe of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To be a giver is bleſſed rather then to be a receiver. Let me open this unto you and ſhew,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>What it is to be a giver?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>What it is to be a receiver?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>What it is to be bleſſed?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Why it is thus bleſſed to be a giver?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. To be a giver here is not to be a giver <note place="margin">Quod me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt tuum efficere nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo iure co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente.</note> out of juſtice, but out of bountie, and mercie. <hi>To give is to make what is mine thine, no outward Law forcing me.</hi> A giver is he that freely makes that which is his to become, another mans.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To be a receiver is he, that accepts as his own, what is given from a right owner; either out of bountie, as when <hi>Solomon</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Queen of Sheba, <hi>or out of mercy,</hi> and when the <hi>poore</hi> receive from the rich.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To be bleſſed, is to be in good caſe or happie ſtate in this preſent world.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:169476:58"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> This you will ſay may diſcourage the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver? </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Not ſo, for it is not our welfare before God, but in the courſe of this life; as when the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed is every one that feareth the Lord, and walketh in his wayes.</hi> How <note place="margin">Pſal. 128. 1. 2, 3.</note> bleſſed? <hi>He ſhall eat the labour of his hands, happie ſhall he be, and it ſhall be well with him: his wife ſhall be as a fruitfull Vine.</hi> In which words you ſee, though he that fears God be bleſſed before God, yet here he ſpeaks of a bleſſedneſſe in this world, that is, an eſtate that is more commodious, and comfortable, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are the barren</hi> in the dayes of perſecution, and baniſhment.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The reaſons why it is thus bleſſed to be a giver, are; 1. Becauſe he that gives feels not the poore receivers troubles, and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. He need not ſay, <hi>What ſhall I eat, what ſhall I drink?</hi> 2. He moſt reſembleth <hi>God,</hi> and <note place="margin">Matth. 6. 31</note> 
                  <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> which is above, which are ſpent, and ſpend, by perpetual bleſſings, and influences. 3: He is in this an <hi>Actor and doer</hi> in the providence of God, whereas the receiver is a ſufferer; and the more active we are, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he more like to God are we, who is a pure act.</p>
               <p>Hence I would perſwade every giver to ſee the excellencie of this eſtate, and to uſe it well. If you ask how this may be done? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; 1. Acknowledge it a dutie to give. The whole courſe of nature receiveth to give. The
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169476:59"/> comfortable ſentence in the laſt judgement is <note place="margin">Matth. 25. <hi>Si non pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſti occid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti.</hi> Dan. 4. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>to givers.</hi> If we give not as we can, we may may be guiltie of murther, therefore <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaid to that great king, <hi>Let my counſel be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to thee, break off thy ſins by righteouſnes, and thine iniquitie by mercy to the poore.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> The co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous man ſaith, May I not do with my own what I will? God may, but not you. You muſt ſay, as <hi>Joſeph,</hi> am not I under God? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> In his own right <hi>God</hi> took from <hi>Laban,</hi> and gave it unto <hi>Jacob, God tooke from the Egyptians and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luke 19.</note> 
                  <hi>gave it to Iſrael;</hi> but you are <hi>Gods ſtewards,</hi> and may not ſay as <hi>Nabal, ſhal I take my meat and my drink, which I have provided for my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vans and gave it unto ſtrangers?</hi> No, no; you know what became of him, know then for certain, as preaching, hearing, prayers are du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſo alſo is the giving.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Labour to give as you ſhould, weigh with me foure things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Who muſt give?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>To whom wy must give?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The order to be obſerved in giving?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>The manner of giving.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. They muſt give, firſt that <hi>own things by</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quod me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt dare.</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 1 Io. 3. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>proper or delegated right.</hi> It muſt be of what, by ſome right <hi>is our own.</hi> Theſe givers are of two ſorts; either they that have <hi>abundance of this worlds goods;</hi> or they that have from hand to mouth. Theſe muſt give in ſome caſes as we ſee <hi>in that poore widdow, who caſt in her</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luke 21. 2 Eph. 4. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>mites; and the labourer who muſt work that he may give to others.</hi> But hence are excluded
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169476:59"/> 
                  <hi>children, ſervants,</hi> and all that have not a right in what is to be given. 2. They that can judge of what they doe, to doe it as a dutie. For it muſt be done with underſtanding, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Hence therefore are excluded mad men who cannot do what they do from well ſetled conſcience; and prodigal fools and children who are under the tuition, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of others.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt give to thoſe <hi>that are Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers,</hi> whether they are friends, or foes. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> If you ask who theſe are? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 1. They are ſuch as Chriſt deſcribes; and are diſtributed into <note place="margin">Matth. 25. 35, 36. Levit. 25. 35. Gal. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Brothers, Believers,</hi> and <hi>Enemies,</hi> if thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my hunger, feed him. 2. Such as we are not forbidden to give unto by the Law of reaſon and conſcience. Now there are 4 ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ask. 1. <hi>Travellers</hi> in their way, like <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 20</note> the wounded man betwixt <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richo,</hi> or the ſtragling <hi>Egyptian</hi> in the field; to <note place="margin">1 Sam. 30. 11, 12.</note> whom <hi>David</hi> gave bread and water. Though theſe may be knaves, yet becauſe we know not their perſons, and their neceſſities, and they may be better then they ſhew for, therefore it is good to give to them, for it is better that ten knaves be relieved, then that one of <hi>Gods ſervants</hi> go emptie away.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Aged</hi> and <hi>Impotent</hi> perſons, as that <note place="margin">Acts 4. Deut. 15. 4. 11. 1 Tim. 5. 4. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Creeple</hi> at the beautiful gate of the Temple, blind <hi>Bartimeus,</hi> and the like. For ſuch <hi>God</hi> provides comfortably in both Teſtaments. Theſe are <hi>Gods</hi> receivers, ſometimes for Chriſts ſake dwelling in them: ſometimes
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169476:60"/> for Gods ſake who created them, and will <note place="margin">Eſ. 58.</note> not have us to forſake the work of his hands: ſometimes for our owne ſake, whoſe fleſh they are.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Bedlams and diſtracted people,</hi> who though I fear that ſome of them are counterfeits, and there be a fault that they wander about, yet becauſe we know nothing certain, and we find how hard it is for diſtracted perſons to work and ſettle; therefore though the man bc overlookt, yet muſt we relieve the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in him from that golden rule, <hi>Do as ye would be done unto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Travellers never out of their way,</hi> who wilfully have no abiding place. Theſe ſurely are non of <hi>Gods</hi> receivers while they are ſuch; and though by importunitie ſometimes they get ſomething from us, and by the negligence of Officers they hunt from us the fat of the true poore; yet their courſe is deteſtable, and not willingly to be maintained, both becauſe they live without <hi>God,</hi> irreligiouſly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out govermnnt, inordinately. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 8.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>order</hi> to be obſerved in giving three texts ſhall direct firſt, ſaith <hi>Paul, If any man provide not for his own, he hath denied the faith,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>and is worſe then an Infidel</hi> in that. Here then is the giver firſt to look, <hi>to his own.</hi> Next ſaith <note place="margin">Deut. 15. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul: Do good unto al, but eſpecially to the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith.</hi> Here the giver muſt next looke, <hi>to the faithful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, ſaith <hi>God, If there be a poore man among you of one of your brethren, thou</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:169476:60"/> 
                  <hi>ſhalt not harden thy heart, nor ſhut thy hand from thy poore brother.</hi> Here the giver muſt in the next place look <hi>to the poore brother,</hi> yet with this exception, that greater preſent neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie calls for it, firſt to thoſe that are furtheſt off from us either in the fleſh, or in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p>Now, laſtly, we are come to the <hi>manner of giving,</hi> which moſtly is ſet down by <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> You muſt give as Chriſts <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 1. 8. 2 Cor. 8. 2. 3.</note> almners; therefore liberalitie is called The <hi>Grace of God.</hi> Ye muſt give richly in affection, and action, according to neceſſitie. Ye muſt give your ſelves <hi>firſt to Chriſt,</hi> and afterwards to others uſes by the will of God. Ye muſt <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 5.</note> give freely; for if there be a willing mind, it is <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 12</note> 
                  <hi>accepted of God.</hi> Ye muſt give ſo, as other men <hi>be not eaſed, and you burthened,</hi> and grieved: for <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 15</note> thus you may be thieves, and murtherers to your ſelves <hi>in doing good to others.</hi> Ye muſt give <hi>in charity,</hi> for otherwiſe all your giving, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note> is as a ſounding braſs, and tinkling cymbal. Ye muſt give <hi>in faith,</hi> believing the promiſe <hi>that God will give it back again,</hi> in kind, or in a <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 9 Prov. 11. 18</note> greater bleſſing. <hi>He that ſoweth righteouſneſſe, ſhall receive a ſure reward.</hi> And that ye may be encouraged, look upon our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>who though he were rich, yet for your ſake he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8 9.</note> 
                  <hi>poore, that ye through his povertie might be rich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus I have plainly pencilled out unto you the Lords building of <hi>a Chriſtian Family.</hi> I have aſcended from the ſquare, to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169476:61"/> 
                  <hi>the timber; from the timber, to the framing; from the framing, to the laying of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; from the foundation, to the upper building; from the upper building, to the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing; from the finiſhing, to the furniſhing; that God may dwel in it and have glory, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you may have comfort and ſay,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Grace, Grace, unto it.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>The Author <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Treatiſe hath publiſhed four other Books, viz.</head>
            <p n="1">1 Mil It for Babes, or a Mothers Catechiſm, wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hief ſaving Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſtian Religion through the Body of it are firſt briefly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, then fully expounded, Laſtly uſefully applied, whereunto is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed 3 Sermons: 1 Secret ſins diſcovered, on Pſalm 19. 12. Who can underſtand his error. 2 On Matth. 13. 45, 46. A Merchant ſeeking Pearls having found a Pearl of great pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, ſold all that he had and bought it. 3 On Pſalm 31. 5. Into thy hand I commit my Spirit, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The yong mans warning piece, a Sermon at the buriall of M. Rogers with a Hiſtorie of his ſinfull life, and woful death, with a diſcourſe of the uſe of ſuch examples.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Foure Sermons: 1 On Iudges 11. 27. The Lord the Iudge be Iudge betwixt the Children of Iſrael and Ammon, 2 On Matthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 7. 12, Whatſoever you would men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them, 3 and 4 On 1 Tim. 1. 19. Holding Faith and a good Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="4">4 A triall of Church forſake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, proving the Church of England to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a true Church, hath a true Miniſtrie and true worſhip. On Heb. 10. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Not forſaking the aſſembling of our ſelves together as the manner of ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All which Books are to be ſold by Philemon Stephens, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the gilded Lion in Pauls Church-yard.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
